<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The charters of London: or, The second part of Londons liberty in chaines discovered. In which by the ancient, rationall, and fundamentall charters of the famous City of London, is proved and declared, that it is the true and undeniable right of all and every the barons, burgesses, free-men, or commoners of London, to have their free vote in chusing out, annually from amongst themselves, a lord major, two sheriffes, and all their alder-men; ... with divers other things worth the knowledg of all the free-men, not only of London, but of all England. For whose good this is published by Lieut. Col: John Lilburn, prisoner in the Tower of London, for the common liberties of the kingdome against the usurpations of the House of Lords.</title>
            <title>London's liberty in chains discovered. Part 2</title>
            <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 179 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88161</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2087</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E366_12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201262</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861789</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861789</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113934</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88161)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113934)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 59:E366[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The charters of London: or, The second part of Londons liberty in chaines discovered. In which by the ancient, rationall, and fundamentall charters of the famous City of London, is proved and declared, that it is the true and undeniable right of all and every the barons, burgesses, free-men, or commoners of London, to have their free vote in chusing out, annually from amongst themselves, a lord major, two sheriffes, and all their alder-men; ... with divers other things worth the knowledg of all the free-men, not only of London, but of all England. For whose good this is published by Lieut. Col: John Lilburn, prisoner in the Tower of London, for the common liberties of the kingdome against the usurpations of the House of Lords.</title>
                  <title>London's liberty in chains discovered. Part 2</title>
                  <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6, 64, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Decemb. 18. 1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes several charters and other documents, as well as introductory and connecting text by Lilburne.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament. --  House of Lords --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Free trade --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Protectionism --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Trading companies --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Civil rights --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  Charters, grants, privileges --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113934:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CHARTERS OF LONDON: OR, The ſecond Part of <hi>Londons
Liberty in Chaines Diſcovered.</hi> In which by the ancient, rationall, and
fundamental Charters of the famous City of <hi>London,</hi> is proved and
declared, that it is the true and undeniable right of all and every the Barons,
Burgeſſes, Free-men, or Commoners of <hi>London,</hi> to have their free
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in chuſing out, annually from
amongſt themſelves, a Lord Major, two Sheriffes, and all their Aldermen;
which Aldermen are annually to be removed by the Commons of every Ward; and
being removed, may not be choſen again for the enſuing yeare, but others by
common conſent are to be put into their places. Alſo it is declared, to be
the right of the ſaid Barons or Common to chuſe the Bridge-maſters,
Chamberlain, Common-Clerk, and Common-Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant, &amp;c. of the City of
<hi>London,</hi> and to be removed by them when they pleaſe. <hi>All which
priviledges, with many others, they are now rob'd of, by their laſt
incroaching, and uſurping, illegall Lord Majors &amp; Aldermen, &amp;c.</hi>
Unto which Charters <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> annexed, a
Diſcourſe, to prove, that though Kings or Parliaments may confirme unto the
people their rights, freedoms, and liberties; yet it lies not in their poweer
to take them from them againe when they pleaſe; no, <hi>not at all:</hi>
becauſe all be truſted powers are (as both Kings &amp; Parliaments, &amp;
all other Magiſtrates whatſoever are,) &amp; ought always to be, for the
good of the Truſters, and not for their miſchief and hurt. In which is
alſo proved, that all <hi>Pattentee-Monopolizing-Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e againſt, and deſtructive to
the fundamental Laws of <hi>England;</hi> and that it is impoſſible for
juſtice, peace, or proſperity, to flouriſh in this Kingdom, till they be
all aboliſhed. With divers other things worth the knowledg of all the
Free-men, not only of <hi>London,</hi> but of all <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For whoſe good this is publiſhed by Lieut. Col: <hi>John
Lilburn,</hi> priſoner in the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> for the common
liberties of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome againſt the uſurpations of the Houſe of
Lords.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Deut. v. 17.19.</bibl> 
               <p>But he ſhall learn to fear the Lord his God, to keep all the
words of this Law, and theſe Statutes, to do them; that his heart be not
lifted up above his Brethren, and that he turn not aſide from the
Commandement to the right hand or to the left.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London. Decemb.</hi> 18. 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:113934:2"/>
            <head>The Printer to the Reader.</head>
            <p>Reader, the ſhortneſſe of time, the abſence of the
Authour, and the difficulty of the Language in the Charter, not being or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
Latin, but ſuch as Lawyers uſe, which is ſo far above my capacity, that
cauſed me to erre when I uſed the beſt skill I could in my Art. Pardon me
therefore (I pray thee) and with thy wiſdome, learning, and good
diſpoſition, help me in this caſe. And for the faults in the
<hi>Engliſh,</hi> the meaneſt capacity may bee helped thus:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 3. <hi>line</hi> 27. <hi>for</hi> Servants r.
Serjeants, p. 32. l. 14. for nay, r. wee. l. 35. r. take undue. p. 33. l. 9.
for bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> be. l. 21. for ity, r. City, p.
36. l. 2. r. is their right. l. 10. for as Magiſtrate. r. as a Magiſtrate
p. 37. l. 1. for Truſtees, r. truſters, l. 4. r. indenoſonizing of a few,
to undenoſonize. l. 8. for divels, r. diveliſh. l. 12. for evill, r. evils.
p. 40. l. 11. r. and intollerable. l. 26. for ſurreptious, read
ſurruptitious, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113934:2"/>
            <head>To the Commons of London, commonly by the prerogative men
thereof, called the Clokemen of London.</head>
            <p>FEllow Citizens, I reade in the 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21. that when
<hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hab</hi> though a King came unto honeſt <hi>Naboth,</hi> not by his
prerogative to take his Vinyard from him, but to deſire it of him (for a
garden of herbes, becauſe it was neere unto his Houſe) for a valuable
conſideration; <hi>Naboth returnes his King this Anſwer, the Lord forbid it
me, that I ſhould give (or part with) the INHERITANCE OF MY FATHERS VN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TO
THEE;</hi> Therefore much more I hope, without offence may you and I ſay to
our prerogative maſters of <hi>London,</hi> who have already robd us by their
meer prerogative pleaſure (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they be far inferiour to the King) not
of our Vinyard, (a ſmall thing in Compariſon) but of our naturall,
rationall, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall, and legall liberties, and freedoms, and ſo as much as
in them lyes, have made us ſlaves and vaſſals to their wills and
plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: by meanes of which they do lay oppreſſions and burthens upon
us, able to breake the backs of Pack-Horſes themſelves, and therefore
ſeeing the knowledge of it in ſome meaſure, is come to our
underſtanding, and dayly every day more and more is likely ſo to do; I hope
it will be no blaſphemy againſt God and the King, nor an Act deſerving
<hi>Naboths</hi> portion, to be ſtoned to death; to ſay unto our
prerogative, uſurping, and incroaching Maſters, <hi>God forbid, that we
ſhould be ſuch villains and traytors to our ſelves, as to ſuffer you to
rob and ſteal from us (and run away with) the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance of our Fathers,
and the Birth-right of us and our children) our Fundamentall Lawes and
Liberties, Franchiſes and Priviledges, that God, Nature, and the juſt
Cuſtomes of the Land in which wee live, hath given us, and for which we have
been fighting above this</hi> 3. <hi>years.</hi> For my part, though all of you
ſhould be ſo ſottiſhly <pb n="2" facs="tcp:113934:3"/> baſe, and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ardly,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and like <hi>Iſſac</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch under your burthens; yet though
I ſhould not find one man amongſt you all of my mind, I am reſolved to
ſend the loudeſt <hi>Hue-and Cry</hi> after them that poſſible I can,
for the regaining of my Liberties, Freedoms, and juſt Priviledges; though I
ſhould by the iniquity of the preſent forſworn, tyrannizing,
oppreſſing, and invaſſalizing times, pay as dear for my ſo doing, as
<hi>Naboth</hi> did for his unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe to part with his Vineyard his
Inheritance.</p>
            <p>My <hi>Hue-and-Cry</hi> after theſe <hi>London prerogative
Robbers,</hi> I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun in my late book, called <hi>LONDONS LIBERTY IN CHAINES
DISCOVERED, printed in Octob. laſt:</hi> the ſecond part of which
<hi>Hue-and-Cry</hi> this preſent diſcourſe is; But here I muſt crave
leave to acquaint you my fellow-Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, that by
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of thoſe many difficulties
which accompanie the Preſſe (wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> makes their proceedings very ſlow) my preſent
<hi>Hue-and-Cry</hi> cannot be ſo loud, as I intended it, becauſe I would
fain have you to have the ſight of ſo much, as herein you ſhall reade,
before the day you chuſe Common-Councell men; after which, you may ezpect an
<hi>APPENDIX</hi> to this Diſcourſe of ſome length, and alſo, all the
reſt of your <hi>CHAPTERS</hi> at large, with obſervations upon them,
deducted from the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall Lawes of the Kingdom: in which Diſcourſe,
you ſhall find ſuch a pack of jugling knavery, as your eyes never read
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>Only this at preſent, I ſhall deſire you to take notice of,
that the City-prerogative Champion, <hi>Irenaeus Lyſimachus,</hi> the Author
of the rotten and putrified book, called <hi>Bellamius Enervatus,</hi> and Col.
<hi>John Bellamy</hi> (a kinſman to the Wethercocks) in his late Anſwer to
the ſaid book, called <hi>Lyſimachus. Enervatus, Bellamius Reparatus,</hi>
and in his <hi>Plea for the Commonalty of London,</hi> ſpends much pains,
<hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con,</hi> to find out, whether or no the L. Major, &amp;
Aldermen of <hi>London</hi> have an abſolute negative voyce in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
Councel; both whoſe Diſcourſes do not at all pleaſe me, nor ſhew the
true rights and priviledges of the Commons of <hi>London:</hi> and therefore, I
ſhall lay down this poſition, and challenge all the
City-prerogative-Champions, to a ſingle combate, to make it good againſt
them all; the Propoſition is this, 
<q rend="inline">that the preſent Lord Major, and the preſent
Court of Aldermen have no right <pb n="3" facs="tcp:113934:3"/> at all, to give any vote at
all in the Comon-Councell, of ſo much as to be preſent there:</q> And my
Reaſons are theſe that follow:</p>
            <p>Firſt of all, the preſent Lord Major is no legall Lord Major,
nor the preſent Aldermen, no legall nor true Aldermen, and therefore have no
true right at all in any ſence to come there; out as De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents to receive
condigne puniſhment, by being disfranchiſed for their uſurpations and
incroachments, as by the Charter of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the 2. they ought, pag.
30, 31, &amp;c. And that the Lord Major is no legall Lord Major, I thus
prove.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe by the 4. Charter of King <hi>John</hi> granted
to the BARONS of <hi>London</hi> (which is every Free man) in the 9 of
<hi>May,</hi> in the 16. year of his raign; and by the Charter of
<hi>Henry</hi> the 3. which you may read in the following Diſcourſe, pag.
28. 29. there is power given to the BARONS OF LONDON, <hi>that they may of
themſelves, chuſe from amongſt them<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
Major,</hi> which priviledge is confirmed by <hi>K. Ed.</hi> the 2. at the
ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deſire of the Major, Aldermen, and the reſt of the Citizens; as
you may read in the 30. pag. following &amp; which priviledge is confirmed to
a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the Citizens of <hi>London,</hi>
by <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> chap. 9. and 1. <hi>E.</hi> 3. 9. 14. <hi>E.</hi> 3.
119. <hi>H.</hi> 4. 1 and by the ſtatutes of <hi>Edward</hi> the 1. called
<hi>articuli ſuper chartas,</hi> chap. 1. <hi>in which ſtatute is alſo a
power given to the Commonalty in every Shire Court, to chuſe the Juſtices
of the Peace for their reſpective Counties;</hi> which ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons have
power by the ſtatutes of the 18. <hi>E.</hi> 1. 8. &amp; 13. chapters, <hi>to
chuſe their own Sheriffes in every Shire;</hi> and this manner of popular
elections is granted to be the right of all the Free-men of <hi>London,</hi> by
both the fore-mentioned Authors. But this Lord Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor is not in the leaſt
legally choſen. Reade the fore-mentioned firſt part of this Diſcourſe,
page 8, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, 13, 14, 15.
<hi>Ergo,</hi> he is no true nor legall Lord Major: And the ſame I ſay of
all the Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My ſecond reaſon to prove the fore-mentioned Propoſition
is this,</hi> becauſe that if the King have no legiſlative power in
himſelf, <hi>as the Parliament proves in their Declarations of the</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>May,</hi> 1642. and 2.
<hi>Novemb.</hi> 1642. <hi>and which begins in the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the
collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Dec. page</hi> 262. 686. <hi>and which Mr</hi> Pryn <hi>much
more praves in the ſecond part of his Soveraign power of Parliaments, p</hi>
73, 74, 75, 76, 77, &amp;c. which book is publiſhed by ſpeciall authority
from <pb n="4" facs="tcp:113934:4"/> the Houſe of Commons, as appeares by the Title page
thereof: now if this be true, then I affirme, he cannot give or depute a
le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlative power to the Lord Major, and Aldermen of <hi>London;</hi> no,
not to his Lords, <hi>who pretendedly call themſelves the Vpper Houſe of
Parliament:</hi> for it is impoſſible, for him to give that to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
which is not inherent in himſelf: But the Lord Major and Court of Aldermen,
for any thing I can perceive, either by their Champion, or any other; lay no
claime to their pretended power of voting to make Lawes in the Common-Councell;
but the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the prerogative-Charter of <hi>Edward</hi> 3. which in
ſuch a caſe is not worth a button.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My third reaſon to prove the propoſition is this;</hi>
becauſe the only and ſole legiſlative Law making power, <hi>is originally
inherent in the people and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>vatively in their Commiſſions choſen by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> conſent, and no other.</hi>
In which the pooreſt that lives, hath as true a right to give a vote, as well
as the richeſt and greateſt; and I ſay the people by themſelves, or
their legal Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions choſen by them for that end, may make a Law or
Lawes to govern themſelves, and to rule, regulate, and guide all their
Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates (whatſoever) Officers, Miniſters, or Servants, and ought not
in the leaſt to receive a Law from them, or any of them, whom they have ſet
over themſelves, for no other end in the world, but for their better being,
and meerly with Juſtice, equity, and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, to execute the
Lawes that they made themſelves, and betruſted them with, as the publique
executors or diſpenſors of. But the Lord Major and Aldermen <hi>(admit
there were no exceptions againſt the manner of their coming into their
Offices)</hi> were never choſen by the Commons of <hi>London,</hi> not in the
leaſt, to ſet in Common-Councell to vote and make Lawes to binde them, but
meerly, and at the moſt, are Officers choſen and betruſted for no other
end at all, but for the better being, peace, and proſperity of the City, to
execute the juſt Lawes of the Kingdome already made in Parliament, by common
conſent of the whole Kingdom; and therefore have no right at all in no
ſence, to ſet in Common-Councell, there to vote, and make Lawes to bind the
Citizens. And therefore, O my fellow-Citizens, I deſire you to bee wiſe,
and looke about you, and not ſuffer theſe <hi>Mungrell, uſurping,
incroaching, pretended Aldermen,</hi> to Lord paramount <pb n="5" facs="tcp:113934:4"/> it
over you, as they uſed to do at your election of your Common-councell men: at
which election, (for any thing I know, or can heare of) they ought not to be
preſent at all, unleſſe they come as particular citizens to give <hi>a
ſingle voyce,</hi> in chuſing their (as well as your) Common-councell men,
whoſe principall office and work it is by vertue of their deputed power
derived from you, to call all your City Magiſtrates, Miniſters, and publick
ſervants, to an account, and to diſ-franchiſe all thoſe that have
endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the deſtruction of <hi>Londons</hi> juſt liberties, and to
know of them what they have done with thoſe many hundred thouſands of
pounds, that yearly is paid into the Chamber of <hi>London,</hi> which ought
principally by right to be laid out to pay or defray the publick charges of the
City, and taxations of the City that are laid upon it by common conſent in
Parliament, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpent in
hugger-mugger, and lai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> out for
ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and put into the pockets
or purſes of ſuch, as it was never
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for. Look to it you Lord Major
and Aldermen, <hi>brethren in evill:</hi> for I profeſſe there is the
moſt notorious jugling and cheating a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, that is amongſt any
generation of men in <hi>England;</hi> which I hope, in the deſpite of you
all, to live in ſome good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to anatomize to my fellow-citizens,
whom, before I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, I ſhall deſire to take notice of foure things, as
the moſt peſtilent evils in the world, amongſt the ſonnes of men, and
they are theſe:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, the Popes unwritten
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ties. Secondly, Kings unlimited
Prerogatives. Thirdly, Parliaments unknown Priviledges. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Lord
Major, Court of Aldermen, and the reſt of the Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative men of Londons
implicit faith, who in the ſecond deſire of their moſt pernitious
Atheiſticall, Papiſticall Remonſtrance, pag.</hi> 7. <hi>would have all
thoſe fully declared againſt, and ſome effectuall courſe ſetled, for
proceeding againſt all ſuch perſons as will not be conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the
publick Diſcipline eſtabliſhed, or to be eſtabliſhed.</hi> What ever
it be, it matters not, although it be never ſo much againſt ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,
reaſon, equity, conſcience, and the word of God.</p>
            <p>By means of ſome of theſe foure, ariſeth all thoſe
Monopoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing and ingroſſing Patentee corporations, that trouble the world:
this poore Kingdome; yea, even this City, <hi>a great number of whoſe
members,</hi> by reaſon thereof, are (as I am informed) for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced 
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113934:5"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> you (my
fellow-citizens) ſeeing your Commo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> upon them to be
imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> power, as they
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> your ſelves,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and let
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and no further
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>oners ſitting in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> power to lay taxes upon you,
and therefore I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the
jurisdiction of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-councell of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, eſpecially ſeing there is
no need nor neceſſity of it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> (as I am informed) that the annual treaſure of the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>London,</hi> is above
five hundred thouſand pounds, which ought to be
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aid out to beare and defray the
publick taxes and burthens of the City, and our own follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Charters
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> how to aſſeſ your
Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament taxes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> preſented
to all you my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to God, and
reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your true and cordiall
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> (and fellow-Citizen) if you
will ſtand for your liberties and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. JOHN LILBURN.</signed>
               <dateline>From my captivity in the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cemb.</hi> 14. 1646.</date> for the common
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>erties of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
invaded by the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurping Lords, &amp;c.</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="charters">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113934:5"/>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
               <div type="charter">
                  <head>CARTAE DE ANNO SE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NDO REG. HEN. 5. Parte ſecunda,
num. 11.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">De Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</note>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>EX
eiſdem ſalutem. Inſpeximus Cartam Dom. <hi>Henr.</hi> nuper Regis patris
noſtri factam in haec verba, <hi>Hen.</hi> &amp;c. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeximus etiam
tenorem Cartae Dom. <hi>H.</hi> quondam Regis Angl. progenitoris no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtri
factam in hac verba:</p>
                  <q> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                        <body>
                           <div type="charter">
                              <opener>
                                 <signed>
                                    <hi>Henricus</hi> Dei gratia Rex Angliae,</signed> 
                                 <salute>Archiepiſcopo Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuar. &amp; Epiſcopis
&amp; Abbatib. &amp; Com. &amp; Baron. &amp; Juſtic. &amp; Vic. &amp; omnibus
fidelibus ſuis Francis &amp; Anglicis totius Angl.
ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutem.</salute>
                              </opener>
                              <p>Sciatis nos <hi>Conceſſiſſe Civibus meis
London. tenend.</hi> Middleſex. per firmam pro 300. <abbr>l.</abbr> ad
compotum ipſis &amp; he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redib. ſuis, de me &amp; heredib. meis. Ita quod
ipſi <hi>Cives ponent Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitem qualem voluerint</hi> de ſeipſis &amp;
Juſtic. quemcunque vel qualem voluerint de ſeipſis ad cuſtoſtienda
placita Coronae meae &amp; eadem placitanda, &amp; <hi>nullus alius erit</hi>
Juſtic. ſuper ipſos homines London. &amp; Cives non placitabunt extra
muros Civita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis pro ullo placito, &amp; ſint quieri de Schot &amp; de Lot.
&amp; de da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negeld, &amp; de murdro &amp; nullus eorum faciat bellum. Et ſi
quis Civium de placitis Coronae implacitatus fuerit (per ſacram quod
iudicatus fuerit in Civitate;) ſe diſrationet. homo London. Et in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fra muros
Civitatis nullus hoſpitetur neque de mea familia, neque de alia vi alicui
liberatur. Et omnes homines London. ſint quie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti &amp; liberi, &amp; omnes
eorum res per totam Angl. et per portus maris de theloneo &amp; paſſagio,
&amp; leſtagio, &amp; omnibus aliis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetud. <pb facs="tcp:113934:6"/>
                                 <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                                    <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                                 </gap> 
                                 <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113934:6"/>
                                 <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                                    <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                                 </gap> 
                                 <pb n="2" facs="tcp:113934:7"/> &amp;
Eccleſiae, &amp; ſinguli Barones &amp; Cives habeant &amp; tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant bene
&amp; in pace ſocas ſuas cum omnibus conſuetud. Ita quod hoſpites qui
in ſocis hoſpitabuntur nulli dent conſuetudines niſi illi cujus ſoca
fuerit, vel miniſtro ſuo quem ibi poſuerit. Et homo London. non judicetur
in ameraiam. pecuniae niſi <hi>ſawere,</hi> ſcil. ad C. s. dico de
placito quod pecuniam ad pertineat. Et amplius non ſit miskennine in
huſtengo, neque in Folkeſmot, neque in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liis placitis infra Civitatem. Et
Huſtengum ſedeat ſemel in heb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; viz. die Lunae. Et terras &amp;
vadimonia &amp; debita Civibus meis habere faciam infra Civitatem &amp; extra,
&amp; de terris de qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ad me clamaverint rectum eis tenebo lege civitatis.
Et ſi quis theloneum vel conſuetud. à civibus meis London. cepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit;
Cives London. in Civitate capiant de Burgo, vel de villa ubi theloneum vel
conſuetudo capta fuerint quantum homo Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. pro theloneo dedit &amp;
proinde de dampno receperit. Et omnes debitores qui civibus London. debita
debent eis reddant in London. vel in London. ſe diſrationent quod non
debent quod ſi reddere noluerint, neque quod non debent ad diſrationand.
ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nire; tunc cives London. quibus debita ſua debentur capiant na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia ſua
in civitate London. de Burgo vel villa, vel de Com. in quo manet qui debitum
debet. Et cives London. habeant fuga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones ſuas ad fugandum, ſicut melius
&amp; plenius habuerint ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſores eorum; ſcil. in Chiltre, &amp;
Middleſex, &amp; Surr,</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>Teſt. Epiſcop. Winton. &amp; Rob.
filio Rich. &amp; Hug. Bigot, &amp; Alvero de Toteney, &amp; Will de Alb.
Spino, &amp; Huberto Reg. Camerario, &amp; Willielmo de Mountfichet, &amp;
Hangulfo de Tanei, &amp; Johanne Bellet, &amp; Roberto filius Sywardi</signed>
                                 <dateline>apud Weſtmonaſt.</dateline>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>Inſpexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus inſuper cartam Dom. Henrici ſecundi quondam
Reg. Angl. progenitoris noſtri factam in haec verba:</p>
                  <q> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                        <body>
                           <div type="charter">
                              <opener>
                                 <signed>
                                    <note place="margin">Hen. 2.</note>H. Rex Angliae,
&amp; Dux Normandiae &amp; Aquitaniae, &amp; Comes Andeg.</signed> 
                                 <salute>Archiepiſcopis, Epiſcopis, Abbatib. Com.
Baron. Juſtic. Vic. Miniſtris, &amp; omnibus fidelibus ſuis Franc. &amp;
Anglis totius Angliae ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem.</salute>
                              </opener>
                              <p>Sciatis me conceſſiſſe Civibus meis London.
quod nullus corum placitet extra muros civitatis London. de ullo placito
praeter placita de tenuris exterioribus, exceptis Monetariis &amp; Miniſtris
meis. Conceſſi etiam eis quietanciam murdri infra ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bem &amp; in
portſoca. Et quod nullus eorum faciat duellum: &amp; quod de placitis and
Coronam pertinentib. ſe poſſint diſrationare ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum 
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113934:7"/> antiquam conſuetud. civitatis praedictae. Et quod infra
muros Civitatis nemo capiat hoſpitium per vim vel per liberati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem
Mareſcalli. Hoc etiam eis conceſſi quod omnes Cives Lond. ſint quieti
de theloneo &amp; leſtagio per totam Angli. &amp; per portus maris, &amp;
quod nullus de amerciam. pecuniae judicetur. niſi ſecundum legem civitatis
quam labuerunt tempore Reg. H. avi mei. Et quod in Civitate in nullo placito
ſit meskeninga, Et quod Huſtingum ſemel tantum in hebdomade teneatur:
&amp; quod terras ſuas &amp; tenuras &amp; vadimonia &amp; omnia debita
juſtè habeant, quicunque eis debeat, &amp; de terris ſuis, &amp;
tenuris quae infra urbem ſunt, rectum eis teneatur ſecundum conſuetudinem
civitatis. Et de omnibus debitis ſuis quae accommodata fuerint apud Lond.
&amp; de vadimoniis ibidem factis placita apud Lond. teneantur. Et ſi quis in
tota Anglia theloneum, vel conſuetudinem ab homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus Lond. ceperit
poſtquam ipſe à recto defecerit vic. Lond. nanium inde apud Lond.
capiat. Concedo etiam eis quod habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant fugaciones ſuas ubicunque eas
habuerint tempore Reg. H. avi mei. Inſuper etiam ad emendationem civitatit;
eis conceſſi quod omnes ſint quieti de Brudtol, &amp; de Childwite, &amp;
de Iereſgiene, &amp; de Scotale. Ita quod Vic. meus Lond. vel aliquis alius
Baillivus ſcotale non fac. Has praedict. conſuetud. eis concedo, &amp;
omnes alias libertates, &amp; liberas conſuet. quas habuerunt tempore Reg. H.
avi mei, quando meliores vel liberiores habuerunt. Quare volo &amp; firmiter
pracipio quod ipſi &amp; heredes eorum haec omnia prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicta hereditarie
habeant &amp; teneant de me &amp; de meis hered.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>Teſt. T. Archiepiſcopo Cantuar. E.
Epiſcopo Lond. Phil. Epiſcopo Bothon. Ern. Epiſcopo Lexon. T. Cancell. R.
de novo Burgo de ſancto Walr. R. de Waren. Wal. Mammot. Ric. de Lucy, Guar.
filio Gerold Mann. Biſet. loc. de Baillolio</signed> 
                                 <dateline>apud
Weſtmonaſt.</dateline>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>Inſpeximus etiam cartam Dom. Ric. primi quon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam Regis
Angliae progenitoris noſtri factam in haec verba.</p>
                  <q> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                        <body>
                           <div type="charter">
                              <opener>
                                 <signed>
                                    <note place="margin">Ri. 1.</note>Ric. Dei gratia,
Rex Angl. Dux Normand. Aquit. Com. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deg.</signed>
                                 <salute>Archiepiſcopis, Epiſcopis, Abbatibus,
Comit. Baronibus, Juſtic. Vic. Miniſtris, &amp; omnibus fidelibus ſuis
Francis &amp; Anglis totius Angliae ſalutem.</salute>
                              </opener>
                              <p>Sciatis nos conceſſiſſe Civibus noſtris
London, quod nullus eorum placitet extra muros civitatis Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. de ullo
placito praeter placita de tenuris exterioribus, excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis monetariis &amp;
miniſtris noſtris. Conceſſimus etiam eis quietan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam <pb n="4" facs="tcp:113934:8"/> murdri infra urbem, &amp; in Portſocha, &amp; quod nullus eorum fac.
duellum. &amp; quod de placitis ad coronam pertinent. ſe poſſint
diſrationare ſecundum antiquam conſuetud. civitatis. Et quod infra muros
civitatis nemo capiat hoſpitium per vim, vel per li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berationem Mareſcalli.
Haec etiam eis conceſſimus quod omnes cives Lond. ſint quieti de teloneo
&amp; leſtagio per totam Angli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, &amp; per portus maris. Et quod nullus de
amerc. pecuniae judicetur, niſi ſecundum legem civitatis quam habuerunt
tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore Regis Henrici avi Henr. patris noſtri. Et quod in Civitate in nullo
placito ſit miskenninga. Et quod huſtingum ſemel tantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in hebdom.
teneatur, &amp; quod terras ſuas &amp; tenuras &amp; vadi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monia, &amp; debita
omnia juſtè habea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t quicun<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> eis debeat &amp; de ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris ſuis
&amp; tenuris quae infra urbem ſunt, rectum eis teneatur ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum
conſuetudinem civitatis, &amp; de omnibus debitis ſuis quae accommodata
fuerint apud London. &amp; de vadimoniis ibidem fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis placita apud London.
teneantur. Et ſi quis in tota Anglia teloneum vel conſuetudinem ab
hominibus London. ceperit poſtquam ipſe à recto d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>fecerit; Vic. London. nanium inde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud
London. capiat. Concedimus etiam eis quod habeant fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaciones ſuas ubicunque
eas habuerunt tempore Reg. H. avi Henr. patris noſtri. Inſuper etiam ad
emendationem civitatis, eis conceſſimus quod omnes ſint quieti &amp; de
Bridtol &amp; de Chid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wite, &amp; de Iereſgiene, &amp; de Schothale. Ita quod
Vic. noſt. Lond. vel aliquis alius Ballivus Scothale non fac. Has praedictas,
conſuetudines eis concedimus &amp; omnes alias libertates &amp; liberas
conſuetudines quas habuerunt tempore Reg. Henrici avi Henr. patris noſtri
quando meliores vel liberiores habuerunt. Quare volumus &amp; firmiter
praecipimus, quod ipſi &amp; heredes eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum haec omnia praedicta hereditarie
habeant &amp; teneant de no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis &amp; Heredib. noſtris.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>Teſt. Hub. Cant. Archiepiſcopo, Rich.
London, Hug. Dunelm. Gilb. Roffenſ. Hug. Lincoln. Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copis. Ran.
Ceſtrenſ. Rich. Com. de Clare, Willielmo Mareſcal. Rog. Bigot. Ganfr.
filio Petri. Hug. Bardof. Wil. Briewer, Willielmo de Waren.</signed>
                                 <dateline>Dat. per manum Willielmi. Elienſ.
Epiſc. Cancel. noſt. apud Winton. 
<date>23. die April. anno regni noſtri
quinto.</date>
                                 </dateline>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>Inſpeximus etiam quandam aliam Cartam ejuſdem Dom. Reg.
Progenit. noſtri factam in haec verba.</p>
                  <q> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                        <body>
                           <div type="charter">
                              <opener>
                                 <signed>
                                    <note place="margin">R. 1.</note>R. Dei gatia Rex
An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliae, <pb n="5" facs="tcp:113934:8"/> Dux Normandiae, &amp; Comes Andeg.</signed> 
                                 <salute>Archiepiſcopis, Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copis, Abbatibus,
Comitibus, Baronib. Juſtic. Vic. Seneſcal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, Caſtellanis,
Conſtabular. Ballivis, Miniſtris, &amp; omnibus fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delibus ſuis,
ſalutem.</salute>
                              </opener>
                              <p>Noverit univerſitas veſtra, nos pro ſalute
animae noſtrae, &amp; pro ſalute animae H. Reg. patris noſtri, &amp;
animarum anteceſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum noſtrorum necnon &amp; pro communi utilitate
civitatis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrae London. &amp; totius regni noſtri; conceſſiſſe,
&amp; firmiter prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepiſſe, ut omnes Kiddelli qui ſunt in Thamiſia
amoveantur u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bicunque fuerint in Thamiſia: &amp; ne de caetero Kidelli
alicubi ponantur in Thamiſia. Quietura etiam clamavimus omne id quod
Cuſtodes Turris noſtrae London. annuatim percipere ſole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant de predictis
Kidellis. Quare volumus, &amp; firmiter praecipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, ne aliquis Cuſtos
prefatae Turris aliquo tempore poſt hoc a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquid exigat ab aliquo nec aliquam
demandam aut gravamen ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve moleſtiam alicui inferat occaſione
praedictorum Kidellorum: ſatis enim nobis conſtat &amp; per venerabilem
patrem noſtrum Hub. Cantuar. Archiepiſcopum, de per alios fideles noſtros
no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis ſufficienter datum eſt intelligi; quod maximum detrimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum &amp;
incommodum praedictae civitati noſtrae London. nec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non &amp; toti regno
noſtro occaſione illorum Kidellorum prove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niebat. Quod ut firmum &amp;
ſtabile perſeveret in perpetuum prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentes paginae inſcriptione &amp;
ſigilli noſtri appoſitione commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivimus.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>His teſtibus. Huberto Cantuar.
Archiepiſcopo. Joh. Wigornienſ. Hug. Coventrienſ. Epiſcopis. Joh.
Comite Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Radolph. Comite Ceſtrenſ. Roberto Comite Leiceeſt.
Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lielmo Comite Arundel, Comite Willielmo Mareſcal. Williel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo de ſanctae
Mariae Eccleſia, Petro filio Herb. Mattheo fratre ſuo. Simon de
Kymaſcherio de Quinceio.</signed>
                                 <dateline>Dat. per manum Magiſtri Euſt. Sarum
Decani Vic. Cancell. tunc agentis. apud Inſulam Andeliac. 
<date>14. die Julii anno Regni noſtri
octavo.</date>
                                 </dateline>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>Inſpeximus etiam Cartam Domini Johannis quondam Reg. Angl.
progenitor's noſtri factam in haec verba:</p>
                  <q> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                        <body>
                           <div type="charter">
                              <opener>
                                 <signed>
                                    <note place="margin">R. Joh.</note>Johannes Dei
gratia Rex Angliae, Dom. Hyberniae, Dux Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandiae, Aquitan. &amp; Comes
Andeg.</signed> 
                                 <salute>Archiepiſcopis, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopis, Abbatib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>s. Com. Baron. Juſtic. Vic.
Miniſtris, &amp; om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus fidelibus ſuis Francis &amp; Anglis
ſalutem.</salute>
                              </opener>
                              <p>Sciatis nos conceſſiſſe civibus noſtris
London, quod nullus eorum placitet <pb n="6" facs="tcp:113934:9"/> extra muros civitatis
London. de ullo placito praeter placita de tenuris exterioribus, exceptis
Monetariis &amp; Miniſtris noſtris: Conceſſimus etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eis quietanciam
murdri infra urbem &amp; in port<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſocha: Et quod nullus eorum fac. duellum,
&amp; quod de placitis ad coronam pertinen. ſe poſſint diſrationare
ſecundum antiquam conſuetudinem civitatis: &amp; quod infra muros civitatis
neque in portſocha nemo capiat hoſpitium per vim vel per libertationem
Mariſcalli. Hoc etiam eis conceſsi. quod omnes cives London. ſint quieti
de teloneo &amp; leſtagio, &amp; omnia alia conſuetud. per om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes terras
noſtras citra mare, &amp; ultra, &amp; per portus maris citra mare &amp;
ultra. Et quod nullus de amerciam. pecuniae judicetur ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi ſecundum legem
civitatis quam habuerunt tempore Reg. Hen. avi Henrici patris noſtri: &amp;
quod in civitate in nullo placito fit miskenninga: Et quod huſtingum ſemel
tantum in hebdomada teneatur, &amp; quod terras ſuas &amp; tenuras, &amp;
vadimonia, &amp; debita omnia juſtè habeant, quicunque eis debeat
&amp; de terris ſuis &amp; te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuris quae infra urbem ſunt; rectum eis
teneatur ſecundum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudinem civitatis, &amp; de omnibus debitis ſuis
quae accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>data fuerint apud Londinum, &amp; de vadimoniis ibidem factis
pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cita apud London. teneantur: Et ſi quis in aliqua terrarum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrarum
citra mare vel ultra, ſive in portubus maris citra mare vel ultra; teloneu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
vel aliquam alium conſuetudinem ab homini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus London. ceperit; poſtquam
ipſe à recto defecerit, Vic. Lond. namium inde apud London capiant.
Concedimus etiam eis quod habeant fugaciones ſuas ubicunque eas habuerunt
tempore Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis H. avi Henr. patris noſtri. Inſuper etiam ad emendationem
civitatis eis conceſsimus, quod omnes ſint quieti de Bridtol &amp; de
Childwite, &amp; de Iereſgiene, &amp; de Scotale. Ita quod Vic. noſtr.
Lond. vel aliquis alius Ballivus Scotale non fac. Has praedictas
conſuetudines eis conceſsimus &amp; omnes alias libertates &amp; libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras
conſuetudines quas habuerunt tempore Regis Henrici avi Henrici patris
noſtri quando meliores vel liberiores habuerunt. Quare volumus &amp; firmiter
praecipimus quod ipſi &amp; heredes eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum haec omnia praedicta hereditarie
&amp; integre habeant &amp; tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant de nobis &amp; heredib. noſtris.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>Teſt. H. Cantuar. Archiepiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copo
Cancell. noſtro. W. London. E. Elienſ. G. Wynton. &amp; G. Roffenſ.
Epiſcopis: Gaufr. filio Petri Com. Eſſex. Williel. Mariſcall. Com. de
Pembroc. Hamel. Com. Waren. Rich. Com. <pb n="7" facs="tcp:113934:9"/> de Clare, Rogero le
Bigot, W. Comite Arundell. Willielmo de Braos. Roberto filio Rogeri, Hug. Bard.
W. Bryeg war. W. de Waren. Stephano de Turneham. Simon de
Pateſhill.</signed>
                                 <dateline>Dat. per manum praedicti H. Cantuar.
Archiepiſcopi Cancell. noſtri a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Sorham 
<date>17. die Junii, anno regni noſtri
primo.</date>
                                 </dateline>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>Inſpeximus etiam quandam aliam Cartam ejuſdem Domini
Johan. factam in hac verba:</p>
                  <q> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                        <body>
                           <div type="charter">
                              <opener>
                                 <signed>Johannes Dei gratia Rex Angliae, Dominus
Hyberniae, Dux Normandiae, Aquitaniae, &amp; Comes Andeg.</signed> 
                                 <salute>Archiepiſcopis, Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copis, Abbatibus,
Comit. Baron. Iuſtic. Vic. praepoſitis &amp; om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus Ballivis &amp;
fidelibus ſuis ſalutem.</salute>
                              </opener>
                              <p>Sciatis nos conceſsiſſe &amp; praeſenti carta
noſtra confirmaſſe, civibus London. Vicecom. Lond. &amp; de Middleſex,
cum omnibus rebus &amp; conſuetudinib. quae pertinent ad praedict. Vicecomit.
infra civitatem &amp; extra per ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras &amp; per aquas: Habend. &amp; tenend.
eis, &amp; heredibus ſuis fina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biliter de nobis &amp; hered. noſtris:
reddendo inde aunuatim nobis &amp; heredib. noſtris tres cent. lib.
Sterlingorum blancorum duobus terminis anni; ſcilicet ad ſcaccar. Paſch.
centum &amp; quinquaginta lib. Et ad ſcaccar. ſancti Mich. centum &amp;
quinquaginta lib ſalvis civibus London omnibus libertatibus &amp; liberis
conſuetud. ſuis. Et praeterea conceſsimus civibus London. quod ipſi de
ſcip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis faciant Viceconi quoſcun<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> voluerint &amp; amoveant quando
vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luerint &amp; eos quos fecerint Vic. praeſentent Iuſtic. noſtris qui
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondeant nobis vel Iuſtic. noſtris ad Scaccar. noſtrum de hiis quae
ad praedictum Vicecom. pertinent ex quibus nobis reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere debent, &amp;
niſi ſufficienter reſponderint &amp; ſatisfecerint; cives London.
reſpondeant &amp; ſatisfaciant de amercia. &amp; firma ſalvis eiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem
civibus libertatibus ſuis, ſicut praedictum eſt. Et ſalvis Vic. eifdem
libertatibus quas alii cives London habent. Ita ſcilicet quod ſi illi qui
pro tempore fuerint Vicecom. conſtituti aliquid delictum fecerint unde
amerciam pecuniae debeant incurrere; non judicentur ad plus niſi ad amerciam.
viginti librarum &amp; hoc ſine dampno aliorum civium ſi Vic. non
fufficiant ad amerc. ſuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſolutionem. Si vero aliquod delictum fecerint,
per quod pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riculum vitae vel membrorum incurrere debeant; judicentur ſicut
judicari debent per legem civitatis: de hiis autem quae ad praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum Vic.
pertinent reſpondeant Vicecom. ad Scaccar. noſtrum coram Iuſtic.
noſtris: ſalvis eiſdem Vic. libertatibus quas alii <pb n="8" facs="tcp:113934:10"/>
cives Lond. habent. Hanc vero conceſsionem &amp; confirmationem fecimus
civibus Lond. propter emendationem ejuſdem civitatis, &amp; quia antiquitus
conſuevit eſſe ad firmam pro recentis libris. Quare volumus &amp;
firmiter praecipimus quod cives Lon. &amp; heredes ſui praedictum Vicecom.
Lond. &amp; de Middelſex, cum omnibus ad praedictum Vicecom. pertin. habeant
&amp; teneant de nobis &amp; hered. noſtris finabiliter, &amp; hereditarie
libere &amp; quiete honorifice &amp; integre per praedictam firmam
treſcentarum librarum: &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibemus ne aliquis civibus London. aliquod
gravamen vel impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimentum, vel diminutionem, de hiis quae ad praedictum
Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com. pertinent vel pertinere folebant facere praeſumat. Volumus etiam
&amp; praecipimus quod ſi nos, vel hered. noſtri, vel aliquis Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtic.
noſtrorum aliquid dederimus vel conceſſerimus alicui de hiis quae ad
firmam praedicti Vicecomit. pertinent. illud civibus Lond. in acquietatione
firmae ſuae ad Scaccar. noſtrum annuatim computetur.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>Teſt. E. Elienſ. S. Bathon.
Epiſcopis. Willielmo Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſcallo, Com. Pembr. Rand. Com. Ceſtrenſ.
Willielmo Com. Arundel. Roberto fillo Walt. Willielmo de
Alben.</signed>
                                 <dateline>Datum per manum H. Cant. Archiepiſcopi,
Canc. noſtri apud bonam villam ſuper Tokam 
<date>5. die Iulii regni noſtri anno
primo.</date>
                                 </dateline>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>Inſpeximus inſuper quandam aliam Cartam praedicti Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni
Iohan. progenitoris noſtri factam in haec verba.</p>
                  <q> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                        <body>
                           <div type="charter">
                              <opener>
                                 <signed>Iohannes Dei gratia Rex Angliae, Dux Hyberniae,
Dux Normandiae, Aquit. &amp; Comes Andeg.</signed> 
                                 <salute>Archiepiſcopis, Epiſcopis, Abbatibus. Com.
Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. Iuſtic. Vic. Seneſcall. Caſtellanis, Conſtabulariis, Ballivis,
Miniſtris, &amp; omnibus fidelibus ſuis ſalutem.</salute>
                              </opener>
                              <p>Noverit univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitas veſtra, Nos pro ſalute
animae noſtrae, &amp; pro ſalute animae H. Reg. patris noſtri, &amp;
animarum anteceſſoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> noſtrorum, necnon &amp; pro communi utilitate
civitatis noſtrae London &amp; totius regni noſtri; conceſsiſſe &amp;
firmiter praecepiſſe, ut omnes Kidelli qui ſunt in Thamiſia vel in
Medeway ubicunque fuerint in Thamiſia, vel in Medeway amoveantur, &amp; ne de
caetero Kidelli alicubi ponan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in Thamiſia, vel in Medeway ſuper
forisfac. decem libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Sterlingorum. Quietum etiam clamavimus omne id quod
Cuſtodes Turris noſtrae London. annuatim percipere ſolebant de praedictis
Kidellis. Quare volumus &amp; firmiter praecipimus ne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquis Cuſtos
prefatae Turris aliquo tempore poſt hoc aliquid exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat ab aliquo nec aliquam
demandam aut gravamen ſive mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiam <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113934:10"/> alicui inferat
occaſione praedictorum Kidellorum: ſatis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim nobis conſtat per venerab
patrem noſtrum, Hub. Cant. Archiepiſcop. &amp; per alios fideles noſtros,
nobis ſufficienter datum eſt intelligi quod maximum detrimentum &amp;
incommodit praedict. noſt. civitati London. neenon &amp; toti regno noſtro
oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſione illorum Kidellorum proveniebat. Quod ut firmum &amp; ſtabile
perſeveret in perpetuum; praeſentis paginae inſcriptione &amp; ſigilli
noſtri appoſitione communimus hiis teſtibus,</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>W. London. E. Elienſ. &amp; W. Winton
Epiſcopis: Gaufr. filio Petri Com. Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex. Willielmo Mariſcall. Com. de
Pembroc. H. Com. Waren. Comite Rogero de Bigot. R. Com. de Clare. Williel. de
Braos, Roberto filio Rogeri. Hug. Bard. W. Briewer. Steph. de Turne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,
Willielmo de Waren, Simon de Pateſhill.</signed>
                                 <dateline>Dat. per manum Hub. Cant.
Archiepiſcopi. Cancel. noſtri apud Sorham. 
<date>17. die Junii, regni noſtri anno
primo.</date>
                                 </dateline>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>Inſpeximus etiam quandam aliam Cartam praefati Dom. J.
factam in haec verba:</p>
                  <q> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                        <body>
                           <div type="charter">
                              <opener>
                                 <signed>Johannes Dei gratia Rex Angl. Dom. Hyber. Dux
Normand &amp; Aquit. &amp; Comes Andeg.</signed>
                                 <salute>Archiepiſcopis, Epiſcopis, Abbaribus, Com.
Baron. Juſtic. Vic. praepoſitis, &amp; omnibus Ballivis, &amp; fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus
ſuis ſalutem.</salute>
                              </opener>
                              <p>Sciatis nos conceſſiſſe &amp; praeſenti
Carta noſtra confirmaſſe Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronibus noſtris de civitate noſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap> London. quod eligant ſibi Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jorem de
ſcipſis ſingulis annis qui nobis ſit fidelis diſcretus &amp; ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus
ad regimen civitatis. Ita quod cum electus fuerit nobis vel Juſtic. noſtro
ſi praeſentes non ſuerimus praeſentetur, &amp; nobis ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret fidelitatem
&amp; quod liceat eis ipſum in fine unni amovere, &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium
ſubſtituere ſi voluerint vel eundem retinere. Ita tamen quod nobis
oſtendatur idem vel Juſtic. noſtro ſi praeſentes non fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimus.
Conceſſimus etiam eiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                                    <desc>•…</desc>
                                 </gap>m
Baronibus noſtris &amp; hac Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta noſtra confirmavimus quod habeant bene
&amp; in pace quiete &amp; integre omnes libertates ſuas quibus hactenus
uſi ſunt tam in ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civitate London. quam extra &amp; tam in aquis quam in
terris &amp; in omnibus aliis locis ſalva nobis Chamberlengeria noſtra.
Quare volumus &amp; firmiter praecipim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>s quod praedicti Barones noſtri civitatis noſtrae London.
eligant ſibi Majorem ſingulis annis de ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſis praedicto modo &amp;
quod omnes praedictas libertates be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne &amp; in pace integre &amp; plenarie cum
omnibus ad hujuſmodi liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates <pb n="2" facs="tcp:113934:11"/> pertinentibus ſicut
praed. eſt.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>Teſtibus dominis, P. Wynton, W. Wigorn.
W. Coventr. Epiſcopis. Wil. Brigwer. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tro filio Herberti. Galfrido de Lucy
&amp; Johanne filio Hug.</signed>
                                 <dateline>Dat. per manum Magiſtri, Ric. de
Hariſcis Canc. noſtri apud No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum Templum Lond. 
<date>9. die Maii, An. Regni noſtri
Sextodecimo</date>
                                 </dateline>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>Inſpeximus inſuper quandam aliam cartam ſupradicti Dom.
J. fact. in haec verba:</p>
                  <q> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                        <body>
                           <div type="charter">
                              <opener>
                                 <signed>Johannes Dei gratia Rex Angliae, Dom. Hyb. Dux
Normand. &amp; Aquit, &amp; Com. Andeg.</signed> 
                                 <salute>Archiepiſcop. Epiſ. Abbatibus. Com. Baron.
Juſtic. Vic. &amp; omnibus Ballivis, &amp; fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus ſuis,
ſalutem.</salute>
                              </opener>
                              <p>Sciatis nos ad petitionem Majoris &amp; Civium
noſtrorum London. Conceſſiſſe &amp; praeſenti Carta confirmaſſe
quod Guilda telaria, non ſit de caetero in Civitate London. nec ullatenus
ſuſcitetur, &amp;c.</p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>Inſpeximus etiam quandam aliam cartam ejuſdem Dom. Hen.
factam in haec verba:</p>
                  <q> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                        <body>
                           <div type="charter">
                              <opener>
                                 <signed>Hen. dei gratia Rex Angliae Dom. Hyb. Dux
Normandiae &amp; Aquit. Comes Andeg.</signed> 
                                 <salute>Archiepiſcopis, Epiſcopis, Abbatibus. Com.
Baron. Iuſtic. Vic. Praepoſitis &amp; omnibus Ballivis, &amp; fidelibus
ſuis ſalutem.</salute>
                              </opener>
                              <p>Sciatis nos conceſſiſſe, &amp; praeſenti
Carta noſtra confirmaſſe, Baron. noſtris de Civitate noſtra London.
quod eligant ſibi Majorem de ſe ipſis ſingulis annis, qui nobis ſit
fidelis diſcretus, &amp; idoneus ad regimen Civitatis. Ita quod cum electus
fuerit, nobis vel Iuſtic. noſtro ſi praeſentes non fuerimus,
preſente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; nobis juret fidelitatem. Et quod liceat eis ipſum in
fine Anni amovere &amp; alium ſubſtituere ſi voluerint, vel eunde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
retinere. Ita tame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quod nobis oſtendatur idem, vel Iuſtic. noſtro ſi
preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes non fuerimus. Conceſſimus etiam eiſdem Baronibus noſtris,
&amp; hac carta noſtra confirmavimus quod habeant bene &amp; in pace li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere
quiete &amp; integre omnes libertates ſuas quibus hactenus uſi ſunt, tam
in Civitate London. quam extra, &amp; tam in aquis, quam in terris &amp;
omnibus aliis locis, Salva nobis Chamberlegeria no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra. Quare volumus &amp;
firmiter praecipimus quod praed. Barones noſtri Civitatis noſtra London.
eligant ſibi Majorem ſingulis an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, de ſe ipſis, praedicto modo; Et
quod habeant omnes praedictas libertates bene &amp; in pace integre &amp;
plenarie cum omnibus ad hujuſmodi libertates pertientibus, ſicut carta dom.
patris noſtri Johannis illuſtris Anglorum Regis quam inſpeximus
rationabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Teſtatur.</p>
                              <closer>Quoad convenit cum recordo 
<signed>Will. Colet</signed> 
                                 <dateline>
                                    <date>7. Octobr.
1646.</date>
                                 </dateline>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:113934:11"/>Inſpeximus etiam cartam dom. E. filii
Regis. E. quondam Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis Angliae progenitoris noſtri factam in haec
verba.</p>
                  <q> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                        <body>
                           <div type="charter">
                              <opener>
                                 <signed>
                                    <note place="margin">Pat. 22. E. 3. p. 2. n.
2.</note>Edwardus dei gratia Rex Angliae, Du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                                       <desc>•…</desc>
                                    </gap> Hyb. &amp; Dux Aquit.</signed> 
                                 <salute>Omnibus ad quos praeſentes literae
pervenerint ſalutem.</salute>
                              </opener>
                              <p>Sciatis quod cum dilecti &amp; fideles noſtri Major,
Aldermanni, ac caeteri Cives Civitatis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrae London. nuper pro meliors
alone civitatis ejuſde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ac pro com. utilitate habitantium in civitate illa,
&amp; confluentium ad eandem quaedam inter ſe ordinaſſent, &amp;
ſtatuiſſent in eadem Civitate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuo obſervanda, &amp; nobis cum
inſtantia ſupplicaſſent ut ea ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptare &amp; confirmare curaremus,
Nos inſpectis quibuſdam lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris com. ſigillo Civitatis illius, ac
ſigillo officii Majoritatis ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Civitatis ſuper praemiſſis
patent. ſignatis, &amp; nobis exhibitis, quoſdam articulos a literis
praedictis elici, &amp; eos in quibuſdam corrigi fecimus, prout inferius
inferuntur videlicet. quod major &amp; Vicecomites Civitatis praedictae per
Cives ejuſdem Civitatis juxta tenorem cartarum progenitorum noſtrorum
quondam Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum Angliae eis inde confecta tum eligantur, &amp; non alio modo,
&amp; quod major Civitatis praedict. in officio Majoritatis illius ultra unum
annum ſimul non moretur. Et quod nullus Vicecomitum Civitatis illius qui pro
tempore erunt, habeat niſi duos Clericos, &amp; duos ſervientes ratione
officii illius, &amp; quod tales clericos &amp; ſervientes ſibi, ſuo
periculo aſſumant, pro quibus voluerint reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere. Et quod Major
Civitatis praed. dum Major fuerit, non habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at aliud officium ad Civitatem
illam ſpectans quam officium Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joratus ejuſdem, nec ſibi attraliat ſeu
coram ipſo teneat placitum vicecomitale in Camera Civitatis illius, nec alia
placita quam illa quae ſecundum antiquam conſuetudinem Civitatis praed.
tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam Major tenere debet. Et quod Aldermanni Civitatis illius de anno in
annum, &amp; praecipue die ſancti Gregorii Papae, per dictam Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munitatem
ſint amobiles &amp; amoti anno ſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti, non re-eligan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ſed loco
amotoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alii eligantur per eaſde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gardas de quibus ſic amoti Aldermanni
fuerunt. Et quod taliagia, vel auxilia ad o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus noſtrum, vel haered.
noſtrorum, ſen pro ſtatu &amp; commodo Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitatis praed. exnunc in eadem
aſſidend. poſtquam per homines gardarum ad hoc electos ſeu deputatos
aſſeſſa fuerunt per Majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem, Aldermannos, ſeu alios n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>n augmententur, nec exaltentur niſi de
com. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſenſu majoris &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munitatis civitatis praed. &amp; quod
denarii de hujuſmodi tallagiis &amp; auxiliis provenientes in cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia 
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113934:12"/> 
                                 <hi>quatuor proborum hominum communariorum</hi> Civitatis
praed. per Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munitatem ejuſde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Civitatis, ad hoc eligendorum liberen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur per
teſtimonium eorundem quatuor hominum ulterius libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand. Ita quod iidem
quatuor homines Communitatem praed. ad quod commodum, &amp; quos uſus denarii
illi devenerint valeant in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formare. Et quod nullus alienigena in libertatem
Civitatis praed. admittatur niſi in huſtengo, &amp; quod indigena, &amp;
praecipue Angli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus mercator de certo miſterio vel officio in libertatem
Civitatis praed. non admittarur niſi per manuc aptionem ſex hominum
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſufficientium, de miſterio vel officio, de quo ille erit
qui in libertatem ſic eſt admittendus: qui quidem ſex homines
manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capiant pro illo ſic admittendo de conſervando Civitatem praed.
indempnem in illa parte &amp; eadem forma manucaptionis obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetur de
alienigenis praed. qui in libertatem Civitatis praed. in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtengo admittendi
ſunt, ſi ſint de aliquo certo meſterio vel officio, &amp; ſi non
ſint de certo meſtero; tunc in libertatem ejuſdem Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis non
admittantur ſine aſſenſu communitatis civitatis illius, &amp; illi qui
in libertatem Civitatis illius, poſtquam regimen regni noſtri
ſuſcepimus contra formas praeſcriptas, ſunt admiſſi &amp; qui
contra ipſorum iuramentum, in hac parte preſtitum, vel contra ſtatum
Civitatis illius venerunt, &amp; inde legitime convincantur; libertate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
amittant Civitatis praed. Salvo ſemper quod de Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiis in eade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>civitate
obſerventur modus &amp; forma antiqui civita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis praed. Et quod ſingulis
annis in praed. civit. quociens opus fuerit inquiratur ſi qui de libertate
ejuſdem civitatis de bonis aliorum, qui non ſunt de eadem libertate in
civitate illa mercandiſas excer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuerint bona illa advocando propria ſua
eſſe contra ipſorum ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramentum, &amp; contra libertatem civitatis praed,
&amp; illi qui inde le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitime couvicti fuerint; libertatem ejuſdem civitatis
amittant. Et quod omnes et ſinguli in libertate civitatis praed. exiſtentes
&amp; li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertatibus ac liberis conſuetud. ejuſdem civitatis gandere
volentes ſint in lotto &amp; Schotto &amp; participes omnium onerum pro
ſtatu ciuitatis ejuſdem, &amp; pro libertate ejuſdem manutenen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum juxta
ſacr. quod fecerunt quando ad libertatem illam admiſſi fuerunt, &amp; qui
hoc noluerit; libertatem ejuſdem civitatis amit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat. Et quod omnes &amp;
ſinguli de libertate civitatis illius exiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp; extra eandem
civitatem manentes, ac per ſe, vel per ſuos, mercandiſas ſuas infra
dictam civitatem excercentes ſint in lotto <pb n="15" facs="tcp:113934:12"/> &amp;
ſcotto cum communariis ejuſdem civitatis pro mercandiſis ſuis praed.
vel aliàs a libertate ſua amoveantur. Et quod co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune ſigil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum
civitatis praed. in cuſtodia duorum Aldermannorum &amp; duo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum aliorum
communariorum per communarios civitatis illius ad hoc eligendorum remaneat
&amp; quod ſigillum illud non negetur pauperibus nec divitibus communariis de
civitate praed. cum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diguerint dum tamen rationabiliter probare poterunt
cauſam ſuaedema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dae &amp; quod pro appopoſitione ſigilli illius nichil
capiatur. Et quod redditiones judicioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in caria civitatis illius &amp;
praecipue poſt veredictum inquiſitionum captarum in caſibus ubi
inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones captae fuerint, non retardentur niſi difficultas
intervenerit, &amp; ſi difficultas intervenerit; propter hoc non remaneant
ultra ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam Cur. faciendae. Et quod pondera &amp; ſtaterae de
mercandiſis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mercatores &amp; mercatores ponderandis de quibus exitus
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venientes &amp; cognitio eorunde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munitatem civitatis praed.
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent in cuſtodia proborum &amp; ſufficientium hominum de eadem
civitate in officio illo expertorum &amp; ad hoc per co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> praed.
eligendorum remaneant ad voluntatem co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munitatis illius cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diend. &amp;
quod aliis, quam ſic eligendis nullatenus comittatur. Et quod vicecomites
civitatis praed. qui prae tempore fuerint thelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neum &amp; alias cuſtumas, ad
firmam ſuam pertinentes ac alia officia publica ad ipſos ſpectantia,
&amp; per alios excercend. ſi ea com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittere voluerint civibus
ſufficientibus pro quibus ipſi viceco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites reſpondere voluerint, &amp;
non aliis committant, &amp; ſi quis per dictos vicecomites ad aliquod
praemiſſorum Deputatus, cuſtumam indebitam capiat vel aliter ſe
geſſerit in officio illo quam debeat &amp; ad ſectam conquerentis inde
convincatur, ab officio illo amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veatur, &amp; juxta ejus demerita pun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                                    <desc>•…</desc>
                                 </gap>tur. Et quod mercatores, qui no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſunt de libertate
civitatis praed. vina aliqua ſeu alia mercimonia infra eandem civitatem ſeu
ſuburbia ejuſdem ad retalliam non vendant: Et quod abbroccatores aliquarum
mercandiſarum in civitate praedicta de catero no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap> exiſtant, niſi per mercatores de meſteris in
quibus ipſi obroccatores habeant officia ſua exercere ad hoc electi fuerint
&amp; ſuper hoc ſaltem coram Majore civitatis praedict. praeſtiterint
juramentum. Et quod omnes hoſpitatores in civitate praedicta, &amp;
ſuburbiis ejuſdem, quam vis non ſint de li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertate civitatis illius,
ſint participes onerum per dictam civitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pro ſtatu ejuſdem manutenendo
contingentium quamdiu ſic fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint <pb n="6" facs="tcp:113934:13"/> communes
hoſpitatores ſicut caeteri hujuſmodi hoſpitatores in civitate &amp;
ſuburbiis praedict. ratione hoſpitalitatum ill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>
                                 <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum participabunt: ſalvo ſemper quod Mercatores de
Vaſcon &amp; alii alienigenae in dicta civitate ad invicem habitare &amp;
hoſpitati poſſint prout hactenus facere conſueverunt. Et quod
cuſtodi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                                    <desc>•…</desc>
                                 </gap> pontis civitatis
praedict. &amp; redditus &amp; proficua ad pontem illum pertinentia duobus
probis &amp; ſufficientibus hominibus de civita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te praedicta aliis quam
Aldermannis ad hoc per co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munitatem civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis illius eligendis ad voluntatem
ejuſdem co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munitatis cuſtodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enda &amp; qui eidem co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munitati inde
reſpondeant &amp; non aliis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittantur. Et quod nullus ſerviens de
Camera Guyhaldae civitatis praedictae capiat feodum de co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munitate civitatis
illius aut execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem faciat, niſi unus per co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munitatem civitatis
praedict. ad hoc electus: Et quod Camerarius, communis Clericus, &amp;
commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis ſerviens civitatis praedict. per co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munitatem civitatis ejuſdem
eligantur &amp; amoveantur pro voluntate ejuſdem Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munitatis. Et quod Major
&amp; Recordator civitatis praedict. ac praedicti Camera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius. &amp; communis
clericus feodis ſuis ratione officiorum ſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum antiquitus ſtatutis &amp;
ſolutis ſint contenti, &amp; alia feoda non capiant pro officiis
ſupradictis. Et quod bona Aldermannorum civitatis praedict. in auxiliis
tallagiis &amp; aliis contributionibus di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctam civitatem contingentibus per
homines de gardis in quibus Aldermanni illi moram fecerint taxentur ſicut
bona caeterorum ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vium de ejuſdem Gardis. Quos quidem articulos prout
ſuperius exprimuntur, &amp; contenta in eiſdem, acceptamus, approbamus,
&amp; ratificamus, &amp; ea pro nobis, &amp; heredib. noſtris quantum in
no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis eſt prefatis civibus heredibus &amp; ſucceſſoribus ſuis
concedimus &amp; confirmamus in civitate &amp; ſuburbiis praedictis ad
communem utilitatem in illis habitantium &amp; confluentium ad eadem obti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nend.
&amp; in perperuum obſervand. Praeterea, volentes Majori Aldermannis. &amp;
civibus civitatis praedict. ad ipſorum requiſitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem gratiam facere
ampliorem; conceſſimus eis pro nobis &amp; here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibus noſtris, quod
Major, Aldermanni, cives, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munitas comu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niariourm civitatis praedict.
&amp; eorum hered. &amp; ſucceſſores pro neceſſitatibus ſeu
utilitatibus ejuſdem civitatis noſtrae inter ſe de ipſorum communi
aſſenſu ſuper bonis ſuis infra civitatem illam ſuper tam redditibus
quam aliis &amp; tam ſuper meſteris quam alio modo quo expedire viderint
tallagia aſſidere poſſint &amp; <pb n="7" facs="tcp:113934:13"/> levare ſine
occaſione noſtri, vel hered. noſtrorum, ſeu miniſtrorum
quorumcun<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> &amp; quod denarii de hujuſmodi tallagiis provenientes in
cuſtodia quatuor proboru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; legal. hominum dictae civitatis per
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munitatem civitatis illius ad hoc eligendoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> remaneant, &amp; extra
ipſorum cuſtodiam pro neceſſitatibus ſeu utilitatibus civitatis
praedict. &amp; non aliter expendantur. In cujus rei teſtimonium, has literas
noſtras fieri fecimus patentes.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>Teſte Meipſo</signed> 
                                 <dateline>apud
Ebor. 
<date>octavo die Iunii, anno regni
duodecimo.</date>
                                 </dateline>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Memorand. quod hi arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur
in Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulis Carta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum de anno 15. E. 3. nu. 12. Per ipſum Reg. &amp; Con.
ſuis in Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amento.</note>Nos autem donationes conceſſiones
confirmationes reſtitutio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes innovationem &amp; ordinationem praedictas
necnon omnia alia &amp; ſingula in Cartis, literis &amp; tenore praedictis
contenta rata haben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp; grata ea pro nobis &amp; heredibus noſtris,
quantum in nobis eſt acceptamus, approbamus, ac pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>atis civibus, &amp; eorum heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus &amp;
ſucceſſoribus civibus civitatis illius tenore praeſentium con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedimus
&amp; confirmamus prout Cartae literae &amp; tenor praedict. plenius
teſtantur. Praeterea volentes eiſdem civibus fuis multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicibus
exigentibus meritis &amp; obſequiis gratiam in hac parte fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere ampliorem;
conceſſimus eis pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> nobis &amp;
heredibus noſtris, quantum in nobis eſt quod licèt ipſi vel
predeceſſores ſui aliqua vel aliquibus libertatum quietancia
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um conceſsionum ordinatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num
liberarum conſuetudinum aut aliorum in dictis Cartis literis &amp; tenore
contentorum aliquo caſu <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mergente
hactenus plene uſi non fuerint, ipſi tamen cives &amp; eorum heredes &amp;
ſucceſſores cives civitatis illius omnibus &amp; ſingulis
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ibertatibus quietanciis
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsionibus ordinationibus liberis conſuetud. &amp; omnibus aliis in
cartis literis &amp; tenore praedictis contentis &amp; eorum quolibet de
cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tero plene &amp; libere gaudeant &amp; ut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>tur in perpetuum ſine occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione vel impedimento noſtri vel
hered. noſtrorum, Iuſtic. Eſcae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum, Vic. aut aliorum Ballivorum, ſeu
Miniſtrorum noſtrorum, vel hered. noſtrorum quorumcumque.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Hiis teſtibus, H. Cantuar. Archiepiſcopo,
totius Angl. Primat. R. London. H. Winton. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vunculo noſtro chariſsimo,
Cancel. noſtro. N. Bathon. &amp; Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenſ. Epiſcopis. Thoma Clarencia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, Iohanne Bedeford, Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frido
Glouceſtr. fratribus noſtris chariſsimis. Edwardo Ebor. conſanguineo
noſtro Ducibus. Edmundo March. Thoma A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rundel Theſaur. noſtro, Richardo
Warren Comitibus. Henr. le Scroop. Henr. Fitzhugh Camerario noſtro. Thoma
Erpingham <pb n="6" facs="tcp:113934:14"/> 
                        <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:113934:14"/> 
                        <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <pb n="6" facs="tcp:113934:15"/> 
                        <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:113934:15"/> 
                        <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <pb n="14" facs="tcp:113934:16"/> Seneſcallo Hoſpitii noſtri militibus, Iohanne
Prophet Cuſtode privati Sigilli noſtri, &amp; aliis.</signed>
                     <dateline>Dat. per manum Reg. apud
Weſtmonaſt. 
<date>12. die Iulii,</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
                  <byline>Per ipſum Regem.</byline>
                  <closer/>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>Convenit cum Recordo,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>WIL. COLLET.</signed> 
                        <dateline>
                           <date>8. die Octob.
1646.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </postscript>
               </div>
               <div type="clause">
                  <head>Clauſae de anno Reg. Henr. ſexti. De pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one
faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enda.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <signed>REX</signed>
                     <salute>Majori &amp; Vicecomitibus London.
ſalutem.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>Cum per Cartas progenitorum noſtrorum quondam Regum Angl.
quas confirmavimus, conceſſum ſit civibus noſtris civitatis prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict.
quod Majorem &amp; Aldermannos de ſcipſis quos voluerint e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligant: &amp;
ipſos, nobis apud Weſtm. non exiſtentibus, Theſaur. &amp; Baron.
noſtris de Scaccario preſentent ut ibidem prout moris eſt admittantur. Ac
jam intellexerimus quod quanquam hujuſmodi electiones per Majorem &amp;
Alderma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nos nec non diſcretiores dictae civitatis, ad hoc ſpecialiter
ſummonitos &amp; praemunitos tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus retroact is fieri conſueverit:
nonnulli tamen qui aliquod in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſe in electionibus hujuſmodi non
habent, nec habere debent; electionibus illis auſu temerario ſe ingerunt
immiſcent &amp; multo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciens electiones quae rite &amp; pacifice fierent,
ſuis validis clamori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus &amp; importunis multipliciter impediunt &amp;
perturbant ad in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentionem quod tales eligantur qui ſuis malefactis &amp;
erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus poſtmodum ſavere poſſent &amp; ea ſub diſſimulatione
dimit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere impunita: quod ſi fieri permittaturin noſtri ac coronae &amp;
dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis noſtrae laſione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nec non ſtatus civitatis praedictae
ſubverſione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> civium<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> noſtrorum ibidem perturbationem &amp;
commotione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deret manifeſte. Nos igitur quieti &amp; tranquillitati populi
nobis ſubjecti providere &amp; congruum remedium in hac parte volentes
adhibere ut tenemur; vobis praecipimus firmiter injungentes quod ante tempus
electionis Maioris civitatis praedictae proxime <pb n="17" facs="tcp:113934:16"/> faciend.
per totam civitatem illam, &amp; libertatem ejuſdem ex parte noſtra publice
proclamari, &amp; firmiter inhiberi fac. ne quis hujuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi electioni niſi
qui de jure, &amp; ſecundum conſuetudinem civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis praedict.
intereſſe debeat illi interſit quovis modo nec ſe de e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectione illa
quoquo quaeſito colore intromittat, neque eſiam im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediat vel perturbet.
Sed quod electio illa per Aldermannos, &amp; alios Cives diſcretiores &amp;
potentiores civitatis paedict. ad hoc ſpecialiter praemunitos &amp;
ſummonitos fiat &amp; habeatur prout ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum conſuetudinem
ſupradictam fuerit faciend. ſcientes pro certo quod ſi quem alio modo
quam ut premittitur electum nobis vell Theſau. &amp; Baronibus de Scaccario
praeſentaveritis illum nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atenus admittemus &amp; omnes illo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> quos contrarium proclamatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis &amp;
inhibitionis praedictarum inveneritis facientes arreſtetis &amp; eos
priſonae noſtrae committatis ibidem moratur quouſque pro eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum
deliberatione duxerimus demandand.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Teſte Rege</signed> 
                     <dateline>apud
Weſtmonaſt. 
<date>7. die Octob.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
                  <closer>Per Concilium. Convenit cum Recordo. 
<signed>WIL. COLET.</signed> 
                     <dateline>
                        <date>8. Octob.
1646,</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:113934:17"/>
               <div type="charter">
                  <head>The Charter of the ſecond yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi>
the fifth, Part. 2. No. 11.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Of the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</note>THE
King to them before ſaid Greeting. We have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood and ſeene a
Charter of Lord <hi>Henry</hi> our father late King of <hi>England</hi> L:
<hi>Henry</hi> made in theſe words, <hi>Henry,</hi> &amp;c. We have ſeen
alſo the Tenour of a Charter of Lord <hi>Henry</hi> ſomtimes King of
<hi>England</hi> our Progenitor.</p>
                  <q> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="charter">
                              <opener>
                                 <signed>
                                    <note place="margin">Hen. 1.</note>Henry by the
grace of God, King of England.</signed> 
                                 <salute>To our Arch-Biſhop of Canterbury, and
Biſhops, and Abbots, and Earles, and Barrons, and Iuſtices, and Sheriffes,
and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his faithfull French and Engliſh of all
England,</salute>
                              </opener>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Know ye</hi> That we have granted to my
<hi>CITIZENS of LONDON,</hi> to hould Middleſex by Farme for 300.
<abbr>l.</abbr> upon accompt, to them and their heires of me and my heires; So
as the ſaid <hi>CITI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ZENS ſhall appoint a Sheriffe whom there they pleaſe
of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and a Iustice whomſoever and what perſon ſoever of
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves they pleaſe, to keepe the</hi> Pleas of my Crowne, which are to
be pleaded for the ſame; 
<note place="margin">Note this 1.</note>
                                 <hi>And none
other ſhall be Juſtice o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the men of London,</hi> and the
<hi>CITIZENS</hi> ſhall not pleade without the walles of London in any plea,
and they ſhall be diſcharged and free of ſcot and lot of daneget and of
murther, and none of them ſhall make warre. And if any <hi>Citizen</hi> bee 
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113934:17"/> impleaded upon pleas of the Crowne, (by oath that he was
adjudged in the City) a man of <hi>London</hi> may diſcharge himſelfe and
within the Walles of the City, none may be lodged, either of my Houſhold,
neither by other force delivered to any, and all men of <hi>London</hi> ſhall
be diſcharged and free (and all their goods) throughout all <hi>England</hi>
and Seaports of <hi>Toll,</hi> and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage and <hi>Laſtage</hi> and all
other Cuſtomes, and the Churches and every the BARRONS and CITIZENS may have
and hould well and in peace their Sokes with all Cuſtomes, ſo that
ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers that do lodge in the Sokes, ſhall pay no Cuſtome but to him
whoſe Soke it is, or to his Servant whom he hath there placed, <hi>&amp; a
man of London ſhall not be Iudged</hi> in the amercements <hi>of mony,</hi>
but according to cuſtome (to wit) in 100. <abbr>s.</abbr> I ſay the pleas
which concerne Amerciaments and miskenning or falſe Iudgement ſhall not be
any more in huſtings nor in folke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote, nor in other pleas within the City,
and the huſtings ſhall ſit once in a week (to wit) on Monday. And I will
cauſe the CITIZENS to have their Lands and Pledges, and what is due unto them
within the City, and without, <hi>And I will do right to them by the Law of the
City for the Lands which they clayme of me,</hi> and if any ſhall take Tole
or Cuſtome of my CI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIZENS of LONDON, 
<q rend="inline">The CITIZENS of London in the City may
take of the Burrough or of the Towne where the Tole or Cuſtome was taken ſo
much as the man of London for Tole gave;</q> And moreover, for his dammage
which he ſhall receive, and all debtors, who owe debts to the CITI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ZENS of
LONDON ſhall pay them in London, or ſhall diſcharge themſelves in
London that they owe not, but if they will not pay the ſame, nor diſcharge
themſelves; Then the CITIZENS of LONDON of thoſe that owed them debts, may
take their <hi>Pledges or Diſtreſſes in the City of London,</hi> of that
Burrough or village, or of that County in which he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bideth who oweth the debt.
And the CITIZENS of LONDON <hi>may have their Chaſes to Chaſe,</hi> as well
and fully as their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors had (to wit) In Chiltre and Middleſex,
and Surrey.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>Witneſſs, Biſhop of Winton, and
Robert the Son of Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, and Hugh Bigot, and Allvero of Totnes, and William
of White-thorne, and Hubard the Kings Chamberlaine, and William of
Mount-Fitcher, and Hangulfe of Taney, and <pb n="20" facs="tcp:113934:18"/> Iohn Bellet, and
Robert the Sonne of Syward</signed> 
                                 <dateline>at
Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter.</dateline>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>Moreover we have ſeen a Charter of our progenitor <hi>Lord
Henry the ſecond,</hi> ſomtime King of England, made in theſe words.</p>
                  <q> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="charter">
                              <opener>
                                 <signed>
                                    <note place="margin">Hen: 2.</note>Henry King of
England, and Duke of Normandy and Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and Earle of Anjou.</signed> 
                                 <salute>To our Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Abbots,
Earles, Barrons, Iuſtices, Sheriffes, Miniſters, and al-our faithfull
Subjects of all England, French, or Engliſh, Gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</salute>
                              </opener>
                              <p>Know ye, that I have granted to my Citizens of
Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, that none of them pleade another without the walles of London,
beſides pleas of forraigne tenures, except my mony Coyners and Servants And
we have alſo granted them a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quittance of murther within the Citty, and in
Porte Soke, and that none of them be inforced to make Duell, and that they may
diſcharge themſelves of pleas belonging to the Crowne, according to the
ancient Cuſtome of the ſaid City, and that within the walles of London none
take up lodging by force, or appointment of the Marſhall. And this alſo I
have granted to them, That all Citizens of <hi>London</hi> be free of Toll, and
Laſtage throughout all England, and Sea-ports, and that none of them be
judged in mercy of mony or amerced, but according to the Law of the City of
London, which it had in the time of King <hi>Henry,</hi> my Grand-father; and
that in the City miskenning or falſe Iudgement be in no plea, and that
huſtings be houlden but weekly, onely once in the week, and that they may
juſtly hould their Lands and Tenures and pledges and all debts, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he
be that is indebted to them, and that right be done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them of their Lands
and Tenures, which be within the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, of all their debts which were borrowed
at London, according to the Cuſtome of the City, and pleas held at
<hi>London,</hi> and of Pledges there made 
<q rend="inline">And if any in all England take toll or
Cuſtome of the men of London,</q> after ſuch ſhall fayle to do right 
<q rend="inline">The Sheriffe of London may take
diſtreſſe thereupon at London, Alſo I grant to them that they have
their Chaſes, whereſoever they had them in the time of my Grandfather King
Henry.</q> Moreover alſo, for the amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the City of London, I have
granted to them, <hi>That all of them be free and diſcharged of
Bridge-toll,</hi> and <hi>Childewite,</hi> and of <hi>Iereſgreene,</hi> and
of <hi>Scotale,</hi> ſo that my <hi>Shrieffe</hi> of <hi>London</hi> or 
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113934:18"/> any other Bailiffe make no Scotale. Theſe ſaid
Cuſtoms I grant, 
<q rend="inline">and all other liberties and free
Cuſtoms which they had in the time of King H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>nry my Grand-father; when they had them better and more free.</q>
Wherefore I will and firmly command that they and their heires may have and
hold of me and mine heires, all the things aforeſaid for Inheritance.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes Thomas Archbiſhop of
Canterbury, Richard Biſhop of London, Phillip Biſhop of Bath, Edward
Biſhop of Exeter, Thomas the Chancelor, R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>bert of Newburgh of St. Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leries, Roger of Warren, Walter
Munmouth, Richard of Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, Gerold Son of Gerold Marm Biſet, Longe of
Ballioll,</signed> 
                                 <dateline>at Weſtminſter.</dateline>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>We have underſtood and ſeene a Charter of our Progenitor
<hi>Lord Richard the firſt,</hi> ſomtime <hi>King of England,</hi> made in
theſe words.</p>
                  <q> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="charter">
                              <opener>
                                 <signed>Richard, by the grace of God, King of England,
Duke of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy, Aquintaine, Earle of Anjou.</signed>
                                 <salute>To our Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Abbots,
Earles, Barrons, Juſtices, Sheriffes, Miniſters, and all our faithfull
Subjects of all <hi>England, French,</hi> and <hi>Engliſh,</hi>
greeting.</salute>
                              </opener>
                              <p>Know ye, that we have granted to our <hi>Citizens</hi>
of <hi>London,</hi> that none of them (except our Coyners and Servants) plead
or ſue without the walles of <hi>London,</hi> of any pleas, beſides
forraign Tenures. <hi>Alſo we have granted to them a diſcharge of Murther
within the City of London, and in Porteſoke,</hi> and that none of them
<hi>be enforced to wage Combat,</hi> and that they may acquit themſelves of
the pleas belonging to the Crowne, according to the ancient cuſtome of the
City, and that none take up any lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing within the walles of the City by
force, or appointment of the Marſhall, Theſe we have alſo granted to
them. 
<q rend="inline">That all Citizens of London be
acquitted and free of Toll, and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtage, throughout England, and all
Seaports,</q> And that none be adjudged in mercy of mony, but according to the
<hi>Law of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> which they had in the time of <hi>Henry, Grandfather
to Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry our Father,</hi> and that miskenning our falſe Judgment in the City
be in no pleas, and that <hi>Huſtings be houlden but once in the week.</hi>
And that they may juſtly have their Lands and Tenures, and Pawnes, and
Pledges, and debts, whoſoever he be indebt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <pb n="22" facs="tcp:113934:19"/> unto them
and right be done to them for their Lands and Tenures which are within the City
according to the Cuſtome of the City, and pleas be houlden at <hi>London</hi>
for all debts which became due and contracted for at <hi>London,</hi> and for
pawnes or weds there made. 
<q rend="inline">And if any in all England ſhall take
Tole or Cuſtome of the men of <hi>London;</hi> after that ſuch a one fail
to do right, The Sheriffe of <hi>London</hi> may take a diſtreſſe
thereupon at <hi>London.</hi>
                                 </q>
                              </p>
                              <p>We grant alſo to them, <hi>that they may have their
Chaſes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they had them in the time of King</hi> Henry,
<hi>Grandfather unto</hi> Henry <hi>Our Father.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>Moreover alſo, for the amendment of the City, we
have grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them; <hi>That all of them be acquit of</hi> Bridtoll, <hi>and
of</hi> Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wite, <hi>and of</hi> Jerriſgreen, <hi>and of</hi> Scotale. So
as our Sheriffe of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> or any other Bayliffe do not make
Scotale.</p>
                              <p>Theſe aforeſaid Cuſtomes we grant to them, and
all other Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and free Cuſtomes, which they had in the time of King
<hi>Henry,</hi> Grandfather unto <hi>Henry</hi> our Father, when they had them
better and more free.</p>
                              <p>Wherefore we will, and firmly command; that they and
their Heires, all theſe aforeſaid, may have and hold as their Inheritance,
and hold of us and our heires:</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>Witneſſes, <hi>Hubert</hi>
Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury, Richard</hi> Biſhop of <hi>London, Hugh</hi>
Biſhop of <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Gilbert</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter, Hugh</hi>
Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln, Ralph</hi> Earl of <hi>Chester, Richard</hi> Earl of
<hi>Clare, William Marſhal, Roger Bygot, Galfride</hi> Son of <hi>Peter, Hugh
Bardolfe, Wil. Brewer, William</hi> of <hi>Warren,</hi>
                                 </signed>
                              </closer>
                              <closer>
                                 <dateline>Given by the hand of <hi>William</hi>
Biſhop of <hi>Ely,</hi> our <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor</hi> at
<hi>Winton,</hi> 
                                    <date>the 23. day of <hi>April,</hi> in the fifth yeare
of Our Reign.</date>
                                 </dateline>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>We have viewed alſo another Charter of Our Progenitor the
ſaid Lord the King, made in theſe words;</p>
                  <q> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="charter">
                              <opener>
                                 <signed>
                                    <note place="margin">Rich: 1.</note>Richard by the
grace of God, King of England, Duke of Norman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, Aquitane, and Earl of Anjou;</signed>
                                 <salute>To Our Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Abbots,
Earles, Barrons, Juſtices, Sherieffes, Stewards, Caſtle-Keepers,
Conſtables, Bailiffes, Miniſters, and all his faithfull ſubjects
greeting.</salute>
                              </opener>
                              <p>
                                 <pb n="23" facs="tcp:113934:19"/>Be it known unto you all, that we
<hi>for the health of our Soule, and for the health of the Soule of King Henry
our Father, and the Soules of our Predeceſſors, and alſo for the common
profit of our City of London, and our whole Realme of England</hi> have granted
and firmly commanded that all the <hi>Weeres which be in the Thames;</hi> be
removed, whereſoever in Thames they be, and from henceforth <hi>Weeres be not
ſet any where in Thames,</hi> we have alſo quite claymed all that which the
Keepers of our Tower of <hi>London</hi> do uſe yeerly to take of the
aforeſaid Weeres, 
<note place="margin">Note this Mr. Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the
Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and give o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver your unjuſt towling of fiſh &amp; other bootes,
ſackbuts, and French Wine, Hogſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads, &amp;c.</note>wherefore we will and
firmly command 
<q rend="inline">that not any Keeper of our Tower
aforeſaid at any time hereafter take any thing of any man, neither bring any
demand, or burthen, or trouble upon any, by reaſon of the ſaid Weeres, for
it is fully made appeare unto us,</q> and by our <hi>Reverend Father Hubert
Archbiſhop of Canterbury,</hi> and other <hi>our faithfull Miniſters;</hi>
we fully underſtand, that great loſſe and diſprofit did come unto our
ſaid City of <hi>London,</hi> and alſo to our whole Realme, by reaſon of
thoſe weeres, <hi>which that it may continue
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                                       <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                                    </gap> and ſure for ever,</hi> we
have confirmed theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents by hand writing and putting to our ſeale
thereto</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe Hubert Archbiſhop of
Canterbury, Iohn Biſhop of Worceſter, Hugh Biſhop of Coventry, Iohn Earle
of Morton, (who was afterward King Iohn) Ralph Earle of Cheſter, Robert Earle
of Leiceſter, William Earle of Arun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del, Earle William Marſhall, William of
St. Maries Church, Peter Son of Herbert, Mathew his brother, Symon of
Ky<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcheir of Rumſay.</signed>
                              </closer>
                              <closer>
                                 <dateline>Given by the hand of Mr.
<hi>Eustace,</hi> Deane of Sarum, Vice-Chancellour, then
being at <hi>the Iſle of Andelazio</hi> 
                                    <date>14. of Iuly 8. yeare of our
Raigne.</date>
                                 </dateline>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>We have ſeen alſo another Charter of our Progenitour
<hi>Lord Iohn late King of England,</hi> made in theſe words.</p>
                  <q> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="charter">
                              <head>King Iohn. Firſt
Charter,</head>
                              <opener>
                                 <signed>Iohn by the grace of God King of England, Lord of Ireland, Duke
of Normandy, and Aquaintaine, and Earle of Anjou.</signed> 
                                 <salute>To his Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Abbots,
Earles, Barrons, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices, Sheriffes, Miniſters, and all our faithfull
ſubjects <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Engliſh,</hi> Greeting.</salute>
                              </opener>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Know ye that we have grantes! to our</hi> CITIZENS
of LON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DON <pb n="24" facs="tcp:113934:20"/> that none of THEM (except our Coyners and
Servants) be impleaded without the walles of the City of any pleas, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
pleas of forraigne Tenures out of the liberties. <hi>We have granted alſo
to</hi> THEM acquittance of murther within the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Suburbs, and that none
of THEM be compelled to wage battayle, and that they may diſcharge THEMSELVES
of the pleas belonging to our Crowne, according to the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Cuſtome of
the City, and that within the walles of the City, nor Subburbs no man take up
lodging by force or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of the Marſhall.</p>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>This we have alſo granted to</hi> THEM, that ALL
THE CI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIZENS of LONDON be aquit of <hi>Tole, and Laſtage, and of all other
Cuſtomes through all our dominions on this ſide of the Sea</hi> and
<hi>beyond.</hi> And that none in mercy of money be judged or amerced, but
according to the Law of the City <hi>which they had in the time of King Henry,
Grandfather of Henry our Father.</hi> And that <hi>misk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>nning or falſe Iudgment,</hi> be not in any pleas in
the City, and that Huſtings be holden onely but once in a week: And that they
juſtly have all their Lands, and Tenures, and Pawnes, and debts of him, who
ever he be that is indebted to them, and that right be holden to them of their
Lands and Tenures which are within the City, <hi>according to the cuſtomes of
the City,</hi> and of all their debts which were borrowed at <hi>London,</hi>
and of Pawnes there made unto them, <hi>the pleas thereof ſhall be houlden at
London,</hi> and if any within any of our Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on this ſide of the Sea,
or beyond, or in any parts of the Sea, <hi>ſhall take any Toll, or any other
Cuſtome of the men of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> after that he ſhall faile to do right.
<hi>The Sheriffe of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don may take therefore a diſtreſſe at
London.</hi> We grant alſo to them, <hi>that they have their Chaſes
whereſoever</hi> they had them in the time of <hi>King Henry Grandfather to
Henry our Father.</hi> Moreover alſo for the amendment of THE CITY, we have
granted to THEM that they be ALL acquit and diſcharged of
<hi>Bridg-toll,</hi> and <hi>Childwite,</hi> and of <hi>Iereſgreene,</hi> and
of <hi>Scotale,</hi> ſo that our Sheriffe of <hi>London,</hi> or any other
Bayliffe, do not make <hi>Scotale.</hi> Theſe aforeſaid Cuſtoms we have
granted to THEM, <hi>and all other liberties and free Cuſtoms which</hi> THEY
<hi>had in the time of King Henry, Grandfather to Henry our Father, when they 
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113934:20"/> had them better, or more free.</hi> Wherefore we will and
ſtrictly command, that THEY and THEIR <hi>Heires,</hi> have fully and for
inheritance, wholly, all theſe aforeſaid, and hold of us and our Heirs.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>WITNESSES H. Archbiſhop of Canterbury
our Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, W. Biſhop of London, E. Biſhop of Ely, G. Biſhop of
Winton; G. Biſhop of Rocheſter, Geffrey ſonne of Peter Earle of
Eſſex, Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Marſhall Earle of Pembroke, Hamel Earle of Warren,
Richard Earle of Clare, Roger le Bigot, William Earle of Arundell, William of
Braus, Robert ſonne of Roger, Hugh Bard, W. Bridgwarren, W. of Warren,
Stephen of Turnham, Simon of Pateſhill.</signed>
                              </closer>
                              <closer>
                                 <dateline>Given by the hand of the aforeſaid H.
Archbiſhop of Canterbury our Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, at Sorham, 
<date>the ſeveneteenth of June, in the firſt yeare
of our reigne.</date>
                                 </dateline>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>We have alſo viewed another certain Charter of the ſaid
<hi>Lord John,</hi> made in theſe words,</p>
                  <q> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="charter">
                              <head>K. Iohns ſecond
Charter.</head>
                              <opener>
                                 <signed>John by the grace of God King of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Lord of Ireland, Duke
of Normandy, Aquitain, and Earle of Anjou.</signed> 
                                 <salute>To his Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Abbots,
Earles, Barons, Juſtices, Sheriffes, Stewards, and all our Bailiffes and
faithful ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, greeting.</salute>
                              </opener>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Know yee, that we have granted, and by this
preſent Charter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed</hi> to the CITIZENS OF LONDON, the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffwick
of Middleſex, with all things and cuſtomes which apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to the ſaid
Sheriffwick, within the Citie and without, by land and by water, to have and
hold to THEM and THEIR HEIRES <hi>for ever, of us and our heires;</hi> paying
there for year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to us and our heires, 300. <abbr>l.</abbr> Sterling Blankes,
at two tearmes of the yeare, <hi>To wit, at the Exchequer at Eaſter,</hi>
150. <abbr>l.</abbr> 
                                 <hi>and at the Exchequer</hi> 150. <abbr>l.</abbr> 
                                 <hi>at
Michaelmas; ſaving to the</hi> CITIZENS OF LONDON all their
<hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>free Cuſtomes.</hi> Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, we have granted
to the CITIZENS OF LON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DON, <hi>That they OF THEMSELVES may make She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffes
whom THEY will, and remove them when they pleaſe;</hi> and that they
preſent theſe whom they make Sheriffes, to our Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices, who may
anſwer to us; as our Barons of the Exchequer, for theſe things belonging to
the ſaid Sheriffwicks, of which they ought to anſwer to us: And if they do
not fully anſwer and ſatisfie <hi>the CITIZENS OF LONDON are to anſwer
and ſatisfie of the Amercement of the Farm;</hi> ſaving to our ſaid
CITIZENS <pb n="26" facs="tcp:113934:21"/> their liberties as aforeſaid, and ſaving to
the ſaid Sheriffes the ſame liberties which other the <hi>ſaid Citizens
of London have,</hi> yet ſo that if thoſe which for the time being ſhall
be appointed Sheriffes, ſhall commit any offence; wherefore they ought to
incurr the mercy of mony, or be amerced, <hi>ſhall be adjudged or condemned
in no more but in forfeiture of</hi> 20. <abbr>l.</abbr> (AND THAT WITHOVT
LOSSE OR PREJVDICE OF OTHER <hi>Citizens.</hi>) <hi>If the Sheriffs be not able
to pay the forfeiture,</hi> But if they commit any offence for which they ought
to undergoe the tryall of life or member, <hi>they are to be judged as they
ought</hi> by the Law of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; But of that which belongs to the
Sheriffwick, the Sheriffes ſhall anſwer in our Exchequer, before our
Barons, <hi>Saving to the ſaid Sheriffes the liberties which other Citizens
of London have.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>This grant and confirmation we have made to our
Citizens of London, for the amendment of the ſaid Citie. And becauſe
an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently it hath been accuſtomed to be let to farm for 300 pounds,
<hi>Wherefore we will and firmly command, that our citizens of London</hi> and
their heires have and hold of us and our heirs for ever, and by inheritance
freely and quietly, honorably and fully, the ſaid She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffwick of London and
Middleſex by the aforeſaid Farme of 300. pound. <hi>And we forbid that not
any preſume to make any let or hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance to the citizens of London of that
which belongs or was accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to belong to the ſaid Sheriffwick.</hi>
Alſo Wee will and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, that if We, our heires, or any of our Juſtices,
have given or granted to any, ought of that which belongs to the Farme of the
foreſaid Sheriffwick; the ſame ſhall be yearly allowed upon ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count in
the Exchequer to the citizens of London, in diſcharge of their Farme.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>WITNESSES. E. Biſhop of Ely, S,
Biſhop of Bath, Willam Marſhall Earle of Pembroke, Rand Earle of
Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, Wil. Earle of Arundel, Robert ſonne of Walt. Will. of
Albans,</signed>
                                 <dateline>Given by the hand of <hi>H. Archbiſhop
of Canterbury</hi> our Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, at <hi>Bona villa upon
Toke.</hi> 
                                    <date>the fifth of July, in the firſt yeare of our
reigne.</date>
                                 </dateline>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>Moreover wee have ſeen another certaine Charter of the
ſaid Lord <hi>Iohn</hi> our Progenitor made in theſe words.</p>
                  <q> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="charter">
                              <head>K. Johns third
charter.</head>
                              <opener>
                                 <signed>Iohn by the grace of God, King of England, Lord of Ireland, Duke
of Normandy, Aquitaine, and Earle of Anjou.</signed>
                                 <salute>To our Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Abbots,
Earles, Barrons, Juſtices, <pb n="27" facs="tcp:113934:21"/> Sheriffes, Stuards,
Caſtle-Keepers, Conſtables, Bayliffes, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and other his
faithfull ſubjects, greeting.</salute>
                              </opener>
                              <p> Be it knowne unto you all, that we for the health of
our Soule, and for the health of the Soule of King Henry our Father, and the
Soules of our Progenitors, and alſo for the common profit of our City of
London, and our whole Realm, have granted and firmly commanded that all the
Weeres which are in Thames or Medewayes, whereſoever they be in Thames or
Medeways, be removed thence and from henceforth no Weeres be ſet any where in
Thames or Medeway, upon for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture of ten pounds ſtarling; We have alſo
quite claimed all that which our Keepers of our Tower of London were wont
yearly to take of the ſaid Weeres; Wherefore we will and firmly command, that
not any Keeper of the aforeſaid Tower; at any time hereafter exact any thing
of any, nor bring upon any, demand, burthen, or trouble by reaſon of the
afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Weeres; for it is clearly made known unto us, by our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend
Father <hi>Hubert Archbiſhop of Canterbury,</hi> and by other our faithfull
ſubject, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                                    <desc>•…</desc>
                                 </gap> it is fully given us
to underſtand, that very great loſſe and diſprofit did come to our
ſaid City, and alſo to our whole Realme, by reaſon of the ſaid Weeres,
which that it may continue firme and ſure for ever; we have confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by our
inſcription of this preſent Charter, and by putting thereto our Seal,</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>Witneſſes, W. B. of London, E.
Biſhop of Ely. W. Biſhop of Winton, Galfride Son to Peter, Earle of
Eſſex, William Mariſcall Earle of Pambroke, Henry Earle of Warwick Earle
Roger of Bigot, R. Earle of Clare, William of Bruce, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Son of Roger, Hugh
Bard, William Brewer, Stephen of Turneham. William of Warren, Simon de
Pateſhill.</signed>
                                 <dateline>Given by the hand of <hi>Hub:
Archbiſhop of Canterbury,</hi> our Chancellor at
<hi>Sorham</hi> 
                                    <date>the 17. day of June, in the firſt year of our
Raigne.</date>
                                 </dateline>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>We have alſo ſeen another certain Charter of the
foreſaid Lord <hi>John,</hi> in theſe words:</p>
                  <q> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="charter">
                              <head>4. K. Iohns fourth
charter.</head>
                              <opener>
                                 <signed>John by the grace of God, King of England, Lord of Ireland, Duke
of Normandy, and Aquitane, and Earle of Anjou:</signed>
                                 <salute>To his Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, Biſhops, Abbots,
Earles, Barons, Juſtices, Sheriffes, Stewards, and his Bailiffes, and
faithful ſubjects, Greeting.</salute>
                              </opener>
                              <p>
                                 <pb n="28" facs="tcp:113934:22"/>
                                 <hi>Know yee, that we have
granted, and by theſe preſent Charters confirmed to our BARONS OF OVR CITY
OF LON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DON,</hi> that THEY May of THEMSELVES chuſe yearly a MAJOR, who is to
us faithfull, diſcreet, and fit for the Government of the Citie;<note place="margin">By which is meant every free man of London. See Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty
in chaines diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, p. 11. 12.</note> ſo that when he ſhall bee
choſen, he ſhall be preſented to us, or to our Iuſtice, if we be not
preſent, and to ſweare to us fidelity; <hi>And that they may at the end of
the yeare remove him, and appoint another, or continue him, if they
pleaſe.</hi> Notwithſtanding ſo, that he be ſhewed to us, or to our
Iuſtice, if we be not preſent. We have alſo granted to our ſaid
<hi>BARONS,</hi> and by this Charter confirmed, <hi>That they may well,
peaceably, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly, and fully have all their liberties which heretofore they
have u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as well in the Citie of London, as without, as well by water as
by land, and in all other places, ſaving to us our Chamberlengarie.</hi>
Wherefore wee will and firmly command, that our ſaid <hi>BA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RONS OF OVR SAID
CITY OF LONDON,</hi> may chuſe yearly to themſelves, a Major of
themſelves, after the aforeſaid manner: and that they may well and in
peace, whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and fully have the aforeſaid liberties with all things ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>ertaining unto the ſaid liberty, as is
aforeſaid.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>WITNESSE the Lords, P. Biſhop of
Winton, W. Biſhop of Wigorn, W. Biſhop of Coventry, William Brigwer, Peter,
ſon of Herbert, Galfride of Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and John ſon of Hugh.</signed>
                                 <dateline>Given by the hand of Mr. <hi>Rich. de
Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſcis</hi> our Chancellor, at the new Temple
<hi>London,</hi> 
                                    <date>9. day of <hi>May,</hi> in the 16. yeare of our
reigne.</date>
                                 </dateline>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>Moreover, we have ſeen another certain Charter of the
fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Lord <hi>John,</hi> made in theſe words:</p>
                  <q> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="charter">
                              <head>K. Iohns fifth
Charter.</head>
                              <opener>
                                 <signed>John by the grace of God, King of England, Lord of Ireland, Duke
of Normandy, and Aquitane, and Earle of Anjou</signed>
                                 <salute>To his Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, Biſhops, Abbots,
Earles, Barons, Iuſtices, Sheriffes, and all our Bailiffes, and faithfull
ſubjects, Greeting,</salute>
                              </opener>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Know yee, that we at the Petition of our Major
and</hi> CITI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ZENS <hi>of London,</hi> have granted, and by this preſent
Charter confirmed, that the Weavers Guild from henceforth be no more in the
citie of London, nor any more revived, &amp;c.</p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>We have alſo ſeen another certain Charter of the ſaid
Lord <hi>Henry,</hi> made in theſe words:</p>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:113934:22"/> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="charter">
                              <opener>
                                 <signed>Henry by the grace of God, King of England, Lord
of Ireland, Duke of Normandy and Aquitane, Earle of Anjou;</signed> 
                                 <salute>To his Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Biſhops, Abbots,
Earles, Barons, Iuſtices, Sheriffes, Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and all our Bailiffes and
faithfull ſubjects, greeting.</salute>
                              </opener>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Know yee, that we have granted, and by this our
preſent Charter confirmed to our</hi> BARONS OF OUR CITY OF LONDON, <hi>That
THEY may of THEMSELVES chuſe every yeare a MAJOR,</hi> who is to us to bee
faithfull, diſcreet, and fit for the government of the Citie: So that when he
ſhall be choſen, he be preſented to us, or our Iuſtices, if we be not
preſent, and ſweare to us fidelity. And that it may be lawfull for them at
the end of the yeare to remove him, and appoint ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or continue him if
they pleaſe; yet ſo as that the be ſhewed to us or our Iuſtices, if we
be not preſent. We have alſo granted to our ſaid <hi>BARONS,</hi> and by
this our Charter confirmed, That they well and in peace, freely, quietly, and
wholly, may have and enioy all their liberties, which heretofore they have
u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as well in the citie as without; as well by water as by land and in
all other places; ſaving to us our Chamberidge. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we will and firmly
command, THAT OUR SAID BARONS OF LONDON MAY OF THEM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SELVES every year chuſe
for THEMSELVES a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior after the aforeſaid manner; and that they may well
and in peace wholly and fully have and enioy all the ſaid liberties, with all
things belonging to the ſame liberties, as the Charter of our Father,
<hi>Lord John,</hi> Noble King of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> (which we have ſeen)
doth rationably teſtifie.</p>
                              <closer>Hitherto this agreeth with the Record. 
<signed>W. COLET.</signed> 
                                 <dateline>
                                    <date>7.
<hi>Octob.</hi> 1646.</date>
                                 </dateline>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p> 
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:113934:23"/>We have alſo ſeen a charter of
<hi>Lord Edward,</hi> ſonne of King <hi>Edward,</hi> late King of
<hi>England,</hi> our progenitor, made in theſe words:</p>
                  <q> 
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="charter">
                              <opener>
                                 <signed>
                                    <note place="margin">Pat. 22. E 2. part 2. n.
3.</note>Edward by the grace of God, King of England, Lord of Ireland, and Duke
of Aquitane:</signed> 
                                 <salute>To all to whom theſe preſent letters
ſhall come, greeting.</salute>
                              </opener>
                              <p> Know yee, that whereas our beloved and truſty, the
Major, Aldermen, and the reſt of the Citizens of our Citie of London, for the
betterment of the ſaid City, and for the common profit of the Inhabitants in
the ſame Citie, and of ſuch as repaire and come to the ſame, did among
themſelves ordaine and enact cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine things to be for ever obſerved in
the ſaid City, and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly ſupplicated us, that we would take care to
accept and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the ſame, we having ſeene certaine letters pattents
touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the premiſes, ſigned with the common Seale of the ſaid City,
and with the Seale of the office of the Majoralty of the ſame City concerning
the premiſes being open and preſented to us; we have cauſed certaine
Articles to be drawne out of the ſaid letters pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, and the ſame in
ſome things to be corrected as here follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they are ſet down, that is
to ſay, <label type="milestone">
                                    <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>1</label> That the Major, and Sheriffs of the
ſaid City be choſen by the Citizens of the ſame City ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the
Tenure of the Charters of our Progenitors for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly Kings of <hi>England</hi>
therefore made unto them, and not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe.
<label type="milestone">
                                    <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>2</label> And the Major of the citie aforeſaid ſhall
not abide in the office of his Majoralty, at one time, above one year.
<label type="milestone">
                                    <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>3</label> And that none of the Sheriffes of the citie
for the time being, have but two Clerks, and two ſervants, in regard of that
office. <label type="milestone">
                                    <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>4</label> And that they take ſuch Clerks and
ſerjeants at their own peril, for whom they will anſwer.
<label type="milestone">
                                    <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>5</label> And that the Major of the citie aforeſaid,
while he is Major, hold no other office belonging to the citie then the office
of the Majoralty of the ſame citie. <label type="milestone">
                                    <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>6</label> Neither
draw unto him, or hold before him in the chamber of the ſaid citie, any
Vicecountill plea, nor any other pleas then thoſe which accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the
ancient cuſtome of the ſaid citie, as Major, he ought to hold.
<label type="milestone">
                                    <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>7</label>
                                 <hi>And that the Aldermen of the ſaid citie
from yeare to yeare,</hi> and eſpecially upon the day of St. <hi>Gregory</hi>
the Pope, <hi>by the ſaid Comonalty be removeble; and being removed, may not
be choſen again for the enſuing yeare.</hi> But in ſtead of thoſe that
bee remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, <pb n="31" facs="tcp:113934:23"/> others be choſen by the ſame Wards of
which the Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſo removed were: <label type="milestone">
                                    <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>8</label> And
that Tallages or Aids for the uſe of us, our heires, or for the State or
profit of the ſaid citie from henceforth in the ſame, to be
aſſeſſed, after they be aſſeſſed by men of the Wards choſen
or deputed for that end, may not be increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or raiſed by the Major,
Aldermen, or others, but by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon conſent of the Major and Commonalty
of the citie afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid. <label type="milestone">
                                    <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>9</label> And that the monies
ariſing from ſuch Tallages, or aids, be delivered in to the cuſtody of
<hi>foure honest commoners</hi> of the citie aforeſaid for that end, <hi>to
be choſen by the commonalty of the ſaid citie,</hi> to be paid over by the
teſtimony of the ſame 4. men; ſo that the ſaid foure men may be able to
inform the ſaid <hi>Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty,</hi> for what profit and what uſes the
ſaid monies went. <label type="milestone">
                                    <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>10</label> And that no ſtranger or
or alien be admitted into the freedome of the ſaid citie, but in the
Huſtings. <label type="milestone">
                                    <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>11</label> And that a Native, and
eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an Engliſh Merchant of any trade or calling, be not admitted
into the liberty of the ſaid citie, but by the manucaption of ſix honeſt
and able men of the trade or c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>lling
of which he ſhall be who is ſo to be made free; which ſaid ſix men
ſhal becom bound for him to be made free, for keeping the citie harmleſſe
on that behalfe. <label type="milestone">
                                    <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>12</label> And the ſame manner or
form of manucaption ſhall be obſerved of the ſtrangers or aliens
aforeſaid, who are to bee made free of the ſaid citie in the Huſtings, if
they be of any cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain trade or office. And if they be of no trade, then they
may not be made free of the ſaid Citie, without the <hi>aſſent of the
Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty of the ſaid citie.</hi> 
                                 <label type="milestone">
                                    <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>13</label> And
they that were made free of the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſince we took upon us the government
of our Realm, contrary to the formes preſcribed, and who againſt their
oathes in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe taken, or againſt the State of the citie have acted
and been lawfully thereof convicted, <hi>ſhall forfeit their freedome of the
citie;</hi> Provided alwayes, that the ancient manner and form of the city
aforeſaid of Apprentices in the ſame citie, be obſerved.
<label type="milestone">
                                    <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>14</label> And that every yeare in the ſaid citie,
ſo often as need ſhall require, inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition be made, if any free-man of
the ſaid citie, ſhall ſell in the citie the goods of others, who are not
free of the citie, by calling thoſe goods their own, contrary to their oath,
and the freedome of the ſaid Citie: thoſe that ſhall be thereof lawfully
convicted, <hi>doe forfeit their freedome of the citie.</hi>
                                 <label type="milestone">
                                    <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>15</label> And that all and every of <pb n="32" facs="tcp:113934:24"/> thoſe which are free of the City aforeſaid, and willing to enjoy
the liberties and free Cuſtomes of the ſaid City, be in Lot and Scot, and
partakers of all charges for the State of the ſaid City aforeſaid, and for
maintaining the freedome thereof, according to the Oath which they did take,
when they were made free, <label type="milestone">
                                    <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>16</label>
                                 <hi>And he that will
not this do, doth forfeit the freedome of the City;</hi> And that all and every
who be free of the ſaid City, and dwell with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſame, and do
exerciſe marchandize by themſelves or A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents within the City, <hi>Be in
Lot and Scot with the Commons of the City for the ſaid Merchandize, or
otherwiſe, they ſhall forfeit their Freedome;</hi>
                                 <label type="milestone">
                                    <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>17</label> And that <hi>main common Seale of the
City</hi> aforeſaid, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the cuſtody of <hi>two Aldermen, and two other
Commoners to bee choſen for it by the COMMONS of the City;</hi> And that the
ſaid Seal be not denyed to the poor; nay, rich Commoners of the City
aforeſaid, whenſoever they ſtand in need of it, while they can
reaſonably prove the cauſe or demand. <label type="milestone">
                                    <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>18</label> And
that nothing be taken for the ſetting to of the ſaid Seal.
<label type="milestone">
                                    <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>19</label> And that Redditions of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the
Courts of the City, and eſpecially after verdict of Inquiſitions taken in
caſes where Inquiſitions are taken, ſhall not be hindered or retarded,
unleſſe ſome difficulty fall out; And if difficulty fall out, yet for
this they ſhall not remain beyond the third Court to be holden after.
<label type="milestone">
                                    <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>20</label> And that weights and meaſures of
Merchandize, to be meaſured betwixt Merchant and Merchant of which the
profits ariſing, and the Cognizance of the ſame, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the
<hi>COMMONALTY</hi> of the ſaid City, remain in the keeping of honeſt and
able men of the City, skilfull in that Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and to be choſen for this by
the <hi>COMMONALTY</hi> of the City to be kept at the pleaſure of the ſaid
<hi>COMMONALTY,</hi> and it to be intruſted by no meanes to any other, but to
ſuch ſo to be choſen. <label type="milestone">
                                    <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>21</label> And that the
Sheriffs of the City aforeſaid for the time being, may ſet the Toll and
other Cuſtomes belonging to their Farm, and other publike offices belonging
to them (and to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed by others) to able Citizens (if they will ſet
them) for whom the Sheriffes themſelves will anſwer, and to none other.
<label type="milestone">
                                    <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>22</label> And if any Deputed to any of the premiſes,
undue cuſtoms, or ſhall otherwiſe behave himſelf, in that office then
he ought, and at the Sute of the Complainant be thereof convicted, <hi>Be put
out of that Office,</hi> and puniſhed according to his demerits.
<label type="milestone">
                                    <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>23</label> And that <pb n="33" facs="tcp:113934:24"/> Marchants who
are not of the Freedome of the City aforeſaid may not ſell any wines, or
other wares within the City or the Suburbs thereof by Retaile. And that B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>okers of any Marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize in the City
aforeſaid may not be, except they be choſen by Marchants of thoſe Trades;
in which theſe Brokers have had their Callings to exerciſe; and upon this
at the leaſt take oath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Major of the ſaid City.
<label type="milestone">
                                    <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>25</label> And that all common Inkeepers in the ſaid
City and Suburbs thereof; though they be not of the Freedome of the City, but
partakers of the charges belonging to the ſaid City, for maintaining the
State of the City, ſo long as they be common Inkeepers; as other the like
Inkeepers in that City and Suburbs ſhall partake, by reaſon of the
Inkeepers; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided alwayes, that Marchants of <hi>Gaſcoign,</hi> and other
ſtrangers al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes may dwell and lodge together in the ſaid City, as
former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they were accuſtomed to do. <label type="milestone">
                                    <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>26</label> And
that the keeping of the <hi>Bridg of the City</hi> aforeſaid, and the Rents
and Profits belonging to the ſaid Bridge, be committed to two honeſt and
able men of the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty aforeſaid, <hi>others then Aldermen,</hi> to be
choſen for that purpoſe, by the <hi>Commonalty of the ſaid City,</hi> to
bee kept at the pleaſure of the <hi>Commonalty of the ſaid City,</hi> &amp;
who are able to anſwer to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monalty of the ſaid ity for the ſame and
not to any others. <label type="milestone">
                                    <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>27</label> And that no Sergeant of
the chamber of Guildhal of the city aforeſaid, take fee of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monalty of
the ſaid City, or make execution, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he be thereunto choſen by
the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monalty of the city for that end. <label type="milestone">
                                    <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>28</label> And
that the Chamberlain, Common-Clark, and Common-Serjeant of the City
aforeſaid, be choſen by the Commonalty of the ſaid City; and removed at
the pleaſure of the ſaid Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty. <label type="milestone">
                                    <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>29</label> And
that the Major and Recorder of the ſaid City, and the ſaid Chamberlain and
Common-Clark, be content with their Fees appointed, &amp; paid of old, by
reaſon of their office: And other fees they may not take for their offices
aboveſaid. <label type="milestone">
                                    <seg type="milestoneunit">article </seg>30</label> And that the Goods of Aldermen
of the ſaid city, be taxed as the Goods of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Citizens, in Aydes,
Tallages, and other Contributions hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening in the city, by men of the Wards,
where theſe Aldermen abide:</p>
                              <p>Which Articles as they are before expreſſed, and
contained in the ſame; we accept and ratifie; And the ſame for us, and our
Heires, as much as in us be, Doe grant and confirme to the ſaid 
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:113934:25"/> Citizens, and their Succeſſors in the City and Suburbs
aforeſaid; for the common profits of thoſe that therein dwell, and of
thoſe that come thither, and the ſame to keep, and for ever to be
obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
                              <p>Moreover, we being willing upon their Petition, to
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer more ample favour upon the Major, Aldermen, and Citizens; have granted
to them for us and our Heires, <hi>That the Major, Aldermen, Citizens, and
Commonalty of the Commons of the City aforeſaid, and their Heires and
Succeſſors; for the neceſſities and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of our ſaid City, by
THEIR COMMON CONSENT AMONG THEMSELVES,</hi> may aſſeſſe Tollage upon
the goods within the City, as well upon Rents, as other goods and as well upon
Trades as any other way, which they ſhall ſee expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and the ſame to
levy without let of us, or our Heires, or our Miniſters whomſoever; And
that the monies ariſing out of ſuch Tallages, remain in the cuſtody of
foure honeſt and lawfull men of the City, to be choſen for it by the
COMMONALTY of the City, and expended out of their cuſtody, for the
neceſſities and profits of the ſaid City, and not otherwiſe. In
Teſtimony whereof, we have cauſed to be made theſe our Letters
Pattents.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>Witneſſe our ſelf</signed>
                                 <dateline>at <hi>Yorke,</hi> 
                                    <date>the 8. Day of June, the 12. Yeare of Our
Raign.</date>
                                 </dateline>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Memorand. thot theſe Articles are
confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the Rolls of the charters of the 15. year. of <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. nu
12. by the King &amp; his Councell in Parliament.</note>We alſo, as much as
in Us is, have accepted, approved, and by the Tenor of theſe preſents, do
grant and confirme unto the ſaid Citizens, and their Heires and
Succeſſors. Citizens of the ſaid Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; the ſaid Gifts, Grants,
Confirmations, Reſtitutions, Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Ordinances aforeſaid; And
alſo, all other things in the Charters, Letters, and Tenor aforeſaid
contained; To have the ſame firme, and ſure for us, and our heires, as the
Charters, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>etters, and Tenor
aforeſaid, do fully teſtifie.</p>
                  <p>Moreover, we are willing to extend more ample favour unto the
full to our ſaid Citizens, which their lawfull merits and ſervices
deſerve; have for Us, and our Heires (as much as in Us is) granted unto them;
That although they, or their Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors by ſome chance falling out,
haue not fully hitherto uſed any, or ſome of the Liberties, Quittances,
Grants, Ordinances, Free-Cuſtomes, and other things in the ſaid Charters,
Letters, and <pb n="33" facs="tcp:113934:25"/> Tenors contained; Nevertheleſſe, the
ſaid Citizens, and their Heires and Succeſſors, Citizens of the ſaid
City; hereafter, may fully and freely for ever enjoy, and uſe all and every
the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Quittances, Grants, Ordinances, Free-cuſtomes, and all other
things in the Charters, Letters, and Tenors aforeſaid contained, of any of
them, without let or hinderance of us and our Heires, Juſtices of Exchequer,
Sheriffes, or other Bayliffes, or our Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, or of the Heires of any of
us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Theſe WITNESSES, H. Archbiſhop of Canterbury,
Primate of all England, R. Biſhop of London, H. Biſhop of Winton our deal
Vncle and Chancellour, N. Biſhop of Bath &amp; Wells; our moſt dear
Brethren Tho: Duke of Clare, Iohn Duke of Bedford, Humphrey Duke of
Gloueeſter, and our cozen Edward Duke of Yorke, Edmond the Marquis, Thomas
Earle of Arundel our Treaſurer, Richard Earl of Warwicke; Sir Henry
Le-Scroope, Sir Henry Fitz-Hugh our Chamberlain, Sir Tho: Eriping<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham Steward
of our Houſhold, Knights; Iohn Prophet Keeper of our Privie-Seal, and
others.</signed>
                     <dateline>Given by the hand of the King at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> 
                        <date>the 12. Day of July.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
                  <byline>BY THE KING.</byline>
                  <closer/>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>This agrees with the Record,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>William Colet.</signed> 
                        <dateline>
                           <date>8. day
of October, 1646.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </postscript>
               </div>
               <div type="clause">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:113934:26"/>
                  <head>A Clauſe of the 11. of King <hi>HENRY</hi> the
Sixth.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <signed>The King</signed>
                     <salute>to the Major and Sheriffes of <hi>London,</hi>
greeting.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>WHereas, by the Charters of Our Progenitors, formerly Kings of
<hi>England, WHICH WE HAVE CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FIRMED.</hi> It is granted to Our Citizens of
Our City afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; That they may chooſe Major, and Aldermen of
themſelves, when they pleaſe, and preſent them to Our Treaſurer and
Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons of the Exchequer, if we be not there, That they may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed there,
as the manner is; And now wee have underſtood, that although is hath been
accuſtomed in times by-paſt, ſuch E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections to be made by the Major and
Aldermen and more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet men of the ſaid City, for the ſame purpoſe
ſpecially ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and warned;</p>
                  <p>Nevertheleſſe, ſome who have no Intereſt in ſuch
Elections, nor ought to have Intereſt in thoſe Elections, but with a raſh
boldneſſe behaved themſelves, do mixe themſelves in, and many wayes
hinder and trouble thoſe Elections (which ſhould be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly and peaceably
made) with their ſtrong and importunate clamours: to the end, that ſuch may
be choſen, who afterwards may favour their wickedneſſe and errours; to
that intent, the ſame be paſſed unpuniſhed: Which if it ſhould be
ſuffered to be done, would manifeſtly tend to the diſhonour of Our Crown
and Dignity: as alſo, the ſubverſion of the ſtate of the City, and 
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:113934:26"/> to the trouble and commotion of our Citizens there; <hi>We
therefore willing (as we are bound) to provide for the quiet and tranquility of
the people,</hi> which are ſubject unto us, and apply a ſitting remedy in
this behalf,</p>
                  <p>We therefore command, and firmly injoyn you; that before the
Elections to be made of the Major of the ſaid city; you cauſe in our Name,
through the whole City and the Liberties thereof, to be proclaimed, and
ſtaictly inhibited, that not any be at ſuch Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; but he that ought of
right by the cuſtome of the city to be preſent at it, by any means, nor by
colour, or ſhift, do get him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in upon the Election, nor hinder or
diſturbe the ſame; But that the Election be made, and had of the Aldermen,
and other more underſtanding and able Citizens of the ſaid city (for it
ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſo warned and ſummoned, as by the cuſtome of the ſaid
ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is to be made) Giving you for ſure to underſtand, that when you
ſhall preſent to us, or to our Treaſurer, being choſen other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe,
then as beforeſaid, <hi>We will in no wiſe allow him.</hi> And all thoſe
whom you ſhall find acting contrary to the prohibition &amp; inhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
aforeſaid;</p>
                  <p>We will and command, and ſtrictly injoyn you, that you
arreſt them, and them commit to our Priſon, there to abide, untill wee
ſhall give Directions for their Deliverance.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Witneſſe the King</signed> 
                     <dateline>at
Weſtminſter 
<date>the 7. day of October.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
                  <closer>BY THE COUNCELL. This agrees with the Record. 
<signed>William Colet.</signed> 
                     <dateline>
                        <date>8.
Octob. 1646.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="discourse">
            <p>This prerogative Proclamation is no Act of Parliament, but only an
Act of the King and his Councell, and ſo of no Authority at all in Law and
Right to null, make void, abridge, or over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the Liberty of the Citizens,
Barons, Burgeſſes, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of <hi>London,</hi> that is, their native
and naturall Rights, and which is eſtabliſhed unto them by the Fundamentall
Law of the <pb n="36" facs="tcp:113934:27"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and, as their popular and univerſall elections is; yea, and which
their right ſo eſſentially, undoubtedly, and firmly, that I ſay, and
will venture my life upon it, to make it good; that neither King nor
Parliament, divided nor conjoyned, cannot juſtly take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the Citizens
of <hi>London,</hi> or any other Citizens in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> their generall,
univerſall, and free voting, in electing of their Major, Aldermen, Sheriffes,
Juſtices of Peace, Recorder, Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain, Town-clark, common-Sergeant,
Bridge-maſter, common-councell men, conſtables or any other Officer
whatſoever that is amongſt them particularly to officiate as Magiſtrate;
for though it be, that Kings and Parliaments may confirme unto a city or
people, their Fundamentall Rights and Liberties, that ſo they may with more
peace, quietneſſe, and freedome enjoy them; yet when they have ſo done,
they cannot take them away againe at their pleaſure; <hi>no not at all,</hi>
without the contracting unto themſelves the odious names of Tyrants and
Oppreſſors; for the Parliament by their own doctrin, (Book Dec. pag. 150.) 
<q rend="inline">are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted by the people to provide for
their Weale, but not for their Woe:</q> So that by right, they cannot make the
people leſſe free then they are, or were, when they found them; but may
make them as much more free, as poſſible they can: and if a Parliament or
any other betruſted Power, ſhould be ſo unnaturall, as to turne the
ſtrength of their Power to ruine, overthrow and deſtroy the Liberties of
thoſe, that impowred, or betruſted them; What doth this elſe, (by their
own doctrine in the fore-mentioned pag.) <hi>but inſtate the people the
impowrers or betruſters, into an abſolute condition of diſobedience, or
non-obſervance of the Precepts, Orders, Injunctions, or Commands of their
impowred Truſtees, or Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates?</hi> unleſſe we think, that
obedience tyes men to deſtroy themſelves, and their Fundamentall naturall
Liberties and Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes; the injoyment of which, makes them to differ from
bruit and ſavadge Beaſts which were never created with reaſon and
underſtand that glorious Image, that God made man in, and ſo made him Lord
over all the creatures in the world beſides him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; but not in the
leaſt, to Lord it over his brother man, without a ſpeciall aſſignation
and mutuall aſſent and agreement, for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter bearing each of other;
and ſuitable to this, is that aſſertion of the Parliament, in their
Declaration; <hi>that all Offices of truſt, are, <pb n="37" facs="tcp:113934:27"/> and
ought to be for the good of the Truſtees.</hi> But extraordinary great are
the evils and miſeries, that this poor Kingdome ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers by
Pattentee-corporations; which, at the beſt, are but an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dennizing of a few,
to undenniſe a many, And to ſpeake pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, <hi>England</hi> being a
Kingdom governed by one Law made by univerſall and common conſent (at
leaſt in pretence) in one Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; all theſe Pattentee-corporations of
what kind ſoever, are moſt illegall, wicked, and Divels make-bates in the
Kingdome, which will never throughly and truly injoy peace, quietneſſe, and
tranquility till they be all utterly anniholated and aboliſhed, and therefore
for the further manifeſtation of their illegalitie, and the evill that accrew
by them to this poor Kingdom.</p>
            <p>I judge it not amiſſe, in the firſt place, here to inſert;
Mr. <hi>Tho: Iohnſon</hi> Merchant his <hi>late printed plea, for Free-mens
Liberties,</hi> which is a moſt excellent piece, and worth the ſerious
peruſall. His Preface to all the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> thus
followeth:</p>
            <q> 
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="plea">
                        <div type="preface">
                           <head>The Preface to all the COMMONS of
<hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>WOrthy Freemen of <hi>England;</hi> The former publique
Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates of this Kingdom, by their Machivilian empoyſoned principles
and ſpecious pretences of common good, (whereas nothing leſſe was
intended) have moſt cunningly &amp; fraudulently cozened you of your native
freedoms, (which by the fundamentall lawes and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of the Kingdom,
ye were born unto) and ſecretly by wicked Pattents have ſtoln away your
Birth-right, to ſet up the particular and ſelf-intereſts of private
ſocieties: One of which I here preſent to your ſerious conſideration,
as a great grievance and burthen, under which, the honeſt Clothier
eſpecially, and thouſands of poor people <pb n="40" facs="tcp:113934:28"/> groan: ye
know for what this Kingdom hath almoſt been waſted to aſhes, ye have
ſpent ſo much of your eſtates and blood, <hi>viz.</hi> the ſubjects
liberty, to which all civill government is ſubſervient. My advice to all is
this, eſpecially the clothiers, and others who are deeply intereſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
that as they love their bleeding dying Country, their deliverance from ſo
great a thraldome; they would by petitioning, and all lawfull meanes, be
earneſt with the Parliament for the removall of this and all other
preſſures.</p>
                           <p>They are bound in duty to God, in juſtice to you, in
diſchareg all of ſo great a truſt committed into their hands; to eaſe
you of all unjuſt grievances, intolerable burthens: Be therefore active in
the work. For very importunities ſake, your indeavours will be crowned with a
hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py ſucceſſe, and (if you faint not) reap the benefit of your labours,
which ſhall alwayes be the deſire of him who is willing to ſerve you.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <dateline>
                                 <date>April, 1646.</date>
                              </dateline> 
                              <signed>THOMAS JOHNSON.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                        <div type="body_of_plea">
                           <p>WHoſoever ſurveyes this Iſland in her radiant and
ſhining luſter with community and freedome, cannot but ſay, <hi>O quant a
mutatio!</hi> Oh how great a change! For indeed, this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is a
Corporation or Society of men under one form of ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill government, made by
common conſent in Parliament, who are all bound by the law, to maintain
common freedome, and the general good of each other.</p>
                           <p>But particulars, Patent-ſocieties, ſwelling with a
Luciferian ſpirit, in deſiring to advance into a higher room then their
fellows, did by ſurreptions Patents incorporate themſelves, excluſively
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came deſtructive to the whole body, and ſubverters of the true ancient
priviledges of the people. And of all ſocieties thoſe of Merchants are the
worſt, having no foundation on the Lawes; The fellowſhip and charter of
thoſe that ſtile themſelves Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of Eaſt-land, is a Monopoly of
this kind, according to the true genuine ſence of the word Monopoly, relating
to a private company, who aſſcribe unto themſelves the ſole exerciſe
and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit <pb n="41" facs="tcp:113934:28"/> of ſuch a Trade, wherein every ſubject
hath equall freedome with them, all which this <hi>Monopoly</hi> doth, and is
illegall, being contrary to <hi>Magna Charta, the Petition of Right, Statutes
of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopolies,</hi> with divers others, and in particular, theſe three
follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
                           <p>The firſt is of the 14. of <hi>Edw. the</hi> 3. 2.
<hi>Item,</hi> where it is contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Great Charter, 
<q rend="inline">That all Merchants ſhall have ſafe
and ſure conduct to go out of the Realm of <hi>England,</hi> and to come, and
abide, and go through the Realm of <hi>England,</hi> aſwell by water, as by
land: we at the requeſt of the Prelates, Earles, Barons, and Commons, will
and grant for us, and for our heires and ſucceſſors, that all Merchants,
Denizens, and Forraigners (except thoſe which be of our enmity) may without
let, ſafely come into the ſaid Realm of <hi>England,</hi> with their Goods
and Merehandize, and ſafely tarry, and ſafely return, paying the
cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, ſubſidies, and other profits reaſonably thereof due; ſo
alwayes that franchiſe and free cuſtomes reaſonably, granted by us and
our Anceſtors to the City of <hi>London,</hi> and other Cities and good Towns
of our Realme of <hi>England,</hi> be to them ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</q>
                           </p>
                           <p>The ſecond is of 18. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. 3. 
<q rend="inline">That the Ordinance made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this
time, upon taking of ſorts of wools in every County be wholly nulled and
defeated, and that every man, aſwel ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, as privie from henceforth
may buy wooll, according as they may agree with the ſeller as they were wont
to do, before the ſaid Ordinances, and that the Sea be open to all manner of
Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, to paſſe with their Merchandize where it ſhall pleaſe
them.</q>
                           </p>
                           <p>By both theſe Statutes, it evidently appeareth, that
every Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhman may tranſport his commodity without moleſtation, to
what Port beyond Sea he pleaſeth, and make ſale for his beſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage,
every Engliſhman being a native Denizen, and privie-man of this Kingdom,
according to the true meaning of the law: for it unreaſonable to me, that the
Law ſhould provide better for Aliens, then her own Children.</p>
                           <p>The third is of 12, <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. 6. <hi>viz</hi> as
followeth: 
<q rend="inline">To the diſcreet Commons in this
preſent Parliament; ſheweth, unto your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet wiſdomes, the
Marchant-Adventurers, inhabiting and <pb n="40" facs="tcp:113934:29"/>
                                 <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                                    <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                                 </gap> 
                                 <pb n="41" facs="tcp:113934:29"/>
                                 <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                                    <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                                 </gap> 
                                 <pb n="42" facs="tcp:113934:30"/> dwelling
in divers parts of this Realm out of the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> that where
they have their paſſage, reſort, courſe &amp; recourſe, with their
goods, wares, and merchandize in divers coaſts and parts beyond the Sea,
aſwell into <hi>Spain, Portugal, Britain, Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Normandy, France, Civil,
Venice, Danske, Eaſtland, Freeze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and other divers and many places,
Regions and Countries being in league and amity with the King our Soveraign
Lord, there to buy and ſell, and make their exchanges with the ſaid goods,
wares, and merchandizes, according to the law and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome uſed in every of
the ſaid regions and places, and there e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very perſon freely to uſe
himſelf to his moſt advantage, without exaction, fine, impoſition, or
contribution to be had or taken of them, to, for, or by any Engliſh perſon
or perſons, &amp;c.</q>
                           </p>
                           <p>By which Statute, all merchants, aſwell thoſe
inhabiting in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers parts of the Kingdom, as of the City of <hi>London,</hi>
as alſo <hi>every free-born ſubject,</hi> is acknowledged <hi>as his Right
to have freedome to trade</hi> to the ſaid parts mentioned, and to divers
other regions and countries, <hi>without ſubjection to any pattent, or paying
any exaction,</hi> fine, &amp;c.</p>
                           <p>For in that the Statute ſaith, <hi>every perſon is
freely to uſe himſelf to his most advantage, without exaction, &amp;c. to
be had or taken of them, or any of them, to, for, or by any Engliſh perſon,
or perſons;</hi> it clearly holds forth, that the merchant, and
conſequently every man that uſeth comerce to theſe parts, <hi>ought not
to come under the obedience of any oppreſſing Corporation
whatſoever.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Now <hi>Dansk</hi> and the <hi>Eaſtland</hi> being
expreſſed in the Statute, which are the principall parts to which theſe
<hi>Eaſtland</hi> Merchants are priviledged by their <hi>Monopoly;</hi> and
indeed, the crowne and glory of the reſt for venting our native commodities;
at alſo the other included, when the Statute ſaith, <hi>and other divers
and many places, regions, and countries;</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>I hope every honeſt man will be willing with heart and
hand to endeavour the <hi>recovery of our Birth-right,</hi> which the Law ſo
evidently makes, our own, from theſe unjuſt oppreſſors.</p>
                           <p n="2">2. <hi>Contrary to the light of nature,</hi> which
teacheth men to walk by congruity and equality, <hi>not to oppreſſe,</hi>
becauſe they would not be oppreſſed, nor to take away a mans
<hi>right,</hi> becauſe they would not have another uſe the ſame
meaſure to them. Which Principles of <pb n="43" facs="tcp:113934:30"/> nature are engraven
upon the hearts of Heathens, who certainly will riſe up in judgment one day
againſt theſe men, <hi>that ſell us for ſlaves in our own
Land.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="3">3. <hi>It is irrationall:</hi> reaſon being the
fountain of honeſt Lawes, gives to every man propriety and liberty: propriety
of intereſt, <hi>freedome of enjoyment and improvement to his own
advantage:</hi> from that propriety take away freedom, and a conſiderable
part is gone: nay we ſee it by experience, that <hi>thoſe who have bereft
us of our li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, have made bold with our propriety:</hi> and indeed, if
Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive may take away the one; why not the other (from the ſame
principles?) So that it appeares to be rationall, <hi>that every native who
hath propriety of goods, wares, &amp; merchandize,</hi> hath freedome <hi>to
tranſport them to any Port beyond Seas,</hi> and there convert them to his
own profit, <hi>it being his true and proper inheritance ſo to doe.</hi> It
is very ſtrange to my underſtanding, that one man ſhould doe the work,
<hi>and another man receive the wages;</hi> I mean, that the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Clothier
who has toyled much in the making of his cloth, ſhall not have the benefit to
ſell it here for his own gain, <hi>or to ſhip it for more profit;</hi> but
being debarred of freedom in both, muſt make ſale to them, in whoſe power
it is to give him <hi>what price they pleaſe,</hi> whereby he is cheated of
the fruit of his labour.</p>
                           <p n="4">4. <hi>That the Monopoly is againſt the honour
of the Nation;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by it the people are put in a condition of
<hi>vaſſalage</hi> in their own country. It takes away <hi>induſtry the
ſpring of wealth,</hi> the hearts of the people being brought to
<hi>ſervility;</hi> and not able by reaſon of this, and other the like
<hi>Patents,</hi> to imploy themſelves, cannot chuſe but procure ſad
effects, if not timely prevented; For</p>
                           <p n="5">5. <hi>The Patent was illegally procured by the
ſolicitation of evill Councellors,</hi> under the Broad Seal of
<hi>England,</hi> in the 21. year of the Raign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> it
bring of no longer ſtanding, under <hi>ſpecious pretences,</hi> as the
profit of her then Majeſty, the good of the Kingdom, &amp;c. whereas by it,
the Natives have been weakned and ſpoyled, which will eaſily appear, if we
conſider theſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</p>
                           <p n="1">1. <hi>By reaſon of this Patent,</hi>
thouſands of poor people are in a condition of beggery, who otherwiſe might
maintain themſelvs in honeſt Callings, by the making of cloath, and other
woollen <pb n="44" facs="tcp:113934:31"/> manufactures, by <hi>Carding, Spinning, Weaving,
&amp;c.</hi> And certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, this one thing throughly conſidered, ſhould
ſtirre up the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of every truly-noble ſpirited <hi>Engliſhman</hi>
to double his ſtrength if it were poſſible, <hi>an hundred fold,</hi> in
all juſt wayes, <hi>for the remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movall of ſo great an
obſtruction,</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="2">2. <hi>The poore Clothier ſuppreſſed,</hi>
none being to trade to thoſe parts but the <hi>Company,</hi> THE CLOTHIER
MAKES NOT HALF THE CLOATHES HE MIGHT: and for thoſe he doth make, they being
of a <hi>confederacy,</hi> and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving all the <hi>priviledge of buying in
their own hands;</hi> by reaſon whereof, <hi>many times he is forced to
ſell them at a farre leſſe price then they coſt him in making,</hi> or
elſe to keep them till the <hi>next year,</hi> which diſcourages and
ſlackens the <hi>Clothier</hi> in the proſecution of his calling, and
cauſes ſome to fail, others to give over, and thoſe which remain many of
them ſcarce can make a living.</p>
                           <p n="3">3. This Monopoly greatly impaireth the trade of
Cloth: thoſe who are judicious, affirme, that 5000. Cloathes more then are,
would be made, ſhipped, and expended yearly in thoſe parts to which they
are authoriſed to trade to; which I verily beleeve, and prove thus: All the
cloth they ſhip, ſome extraordinary times excepted, is but to one or two
Townes, and there reſiding their Factors, who making ſale to the Burger,
hee ſendeth the cloth up &amp; down the Countrey, whence ariſeth many
miſchiefs, the countries not being furniſhed as they ſhould, as alſo
the ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at <hi>ſuch exceſſive rates,</hi> cauſeth the
<hi>Dutch</hi> to make cloath in an abundant manner, and to be ſatisfied with
it, though it be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding courſe. And again, there being divers
<hi>Kingdomes, Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, Dukedomes, Countries, Cities,</hi> and
<hi>Townes,</hi> to which by their <hi>Patent</hi> they are licenced, what
advantage would the young merchant have, having ſo vaſt a compaſſe, how
active would hee be from Town to Town, from Citie to Citie, from one Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey
to another, and SELLING CHEAP, would invite forraigne parties to ſet a true
eſtimate upon our native commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities. And certainly were trade free,
<hi>Sweedland</hi> and <hi>Pomerland</hi> would vent much cloath; whereas the
Company is not able to ſatisfie <hi>Eaſtland</hi> it ſelfe, by reaſon
of the ſmalneſſe of their ſtock; it may be eaſily conceived, that
ſuch a ſmall company of <hi>Private men,</hi> are never able to ſuffice
ſuch famous <hi>Kingdomes</hi> and <hi>Duke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes</hi> 
                              <pb n="45" facs="tcp:113934:31"/>
to which they onely are <hi>licenſed</hi> to traffick.</p>
                           <p n="6">6. It cauſeth a great decay of
<hi>Navigation,</hi> which ſuſtaineth the <hi>Mariners,</hi> ſo that by
this and other the like Patents, the <hi>Saylor is greatly ſupprest.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="7">7. It obſtructeth Returnes, divers of the moſt
ſtaple commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities which our countrey ſtands in need of, are imported by
them, <hi>viz. Flax, Hemr, Pot-aſhes, Pitch, Tarre, Courſe Linnen, Packing
Canvas,</hi> with divers other very conſiderable merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize: now they bring
over when they pleaſe, and what they pleaſe, <hi>and ſell at what price
they pleaſe,</hi> which cannot but have ſundry evill concomitance, 1. Our
Country is not ſatisfied with that variety and conveniency it ſhould: and
2. By reaſon the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizen gives ſuch an unreaſonable rate to the
Merchant, the poore have all exceſſive deare, giving halfe as much more
then the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity is worth, or then it would be ſold for, were the trade
but open, from which and ſuch other dealings it is, that the people are
unconſcionably waſted and weakned: and threfore what ere it coſt us,
<hi>lets have this ravenous patent down:</hi> whereby there would be all
theſe ſix gallant effects 1. <hi>Multitudes of poor main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</hi> 2.
<hi>The Clothier raiſed.</hi> 3. <hi>The trade of cloath greatly augmented,
by reaſons that thouſands might be vented more then are.</hi> 4. <hi>The
number of Merchants increaſed.</hi> 5. <hi>The Art of Navigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
furthered.</hi> 6. <hi>And laſtly, an univerſall benefit to the whole
na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> from the plenty of merchandiz imported, which we ſhould have at
farre eaſier and more valuable conſiderations.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Object.</hi> But if trade be free, the Alien will
expect freedome alſo.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Anſw.</hi> I ſee no ground but aliens paying
cuſtome, provided alwayes that wee enjoy as full and large priviledges with
them, they ought to have the like here with us. But ſecondly, ſuppoſe the
State ſhould prohibit ſtrangers yet there is no ſhadow or colour of right
reaſon, that we who have equall liberties in the lawes, have ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tured our
eſtates &amp; lives ſo freely to preſerve them, ſhould be deprived of
our true inheritance: &amp; therfore for further ſatisfaction, I ſhall here
inſert part of their Charter, that every one may judge whether it be juſt
or no.</p>
                           <q> 
                              <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                                 <body>
                                    <div type="charter">
                                       <p>Foraſmuch as we be credibly informed, &amp;c.
that you our Subjects, Merchants and others, exerciſing and uſing the
traffick and feat of Merchandiſe, <pb n="46" facs="tcp:113934:32"/> out and from any our
Dominions through the <hi>Sound,</hi> into the Realmes, Kingdomes, Dominions,
Dukedomes, Countries, Cities and Townes of <hi>Norway, Swethia, Poland,</hi>
and the terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories of the ſame Kingdomes: as alſo into <hi>Letto,</hi>
and <hi>Liefland,</hi> under the dominion of the King of <hi>Pole,
Pruſſia,</hi> and alſo <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merland,</hi> from the river of
<hi>Odera</hi> Eaſtward, and alſo <hi>Ry</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill</hi> in
<hi>Liefland</hi> aforeſaid, <hi>Kingsbrough, Elbinge, Brownſbrough,</hi>
and <hi>Danſick</hi> in <hi>Bruſia, Copenhaven</hi> and <hi>Elſenore</hi>
in <hi>Danſk:</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the <hi>Nerve,</hi> and the territories thereof
belonging: as: alſo into the Iſland of <hi>Finland, Goteland, Eweland,</hi>
and <hi>Burutholme</hi> within the <hi>Sound</hi> aforeſaid, by one conſent
are willing to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and aſſemble your ſelves into one fellowſhip,
and to be one body incorporate and politick, in deed and in name; Wee
conſidering that your purpoſes in this behalf are very laudable, doe
therefore not onely approve and ratifie the ſame, but will you to perſevere
in your good minds and purpoſes, to the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment and perfection
thereof, and earneſtly deſiring that our Merchants and their
ſucceſſors haunting the ſaid King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, Dominions, Countries, Cities
and Townes before mentioned, or any of them, for merchandize, in and through
the <hi>Sound</hi> of the Kingdome of <hi>Denmark</hi> (except before excepted)
may from henceforth profit and increaſe as proſperouſly as any Merchants
of this land have aforetime increaſed and profited: And do grant for us, our
heires and ſucceſſors, that from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth there be and ſhall be of
the ſaid fellowſhip, one GO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VERNOR, one DEPUTY, or DEPUTIES, and foure and
twenty ASSISTANTS of the ſaid fellowſhip; and that they, or the major part
of them may make Statutes, Lawes and Ordinances; and that the aforeſaid
Governor, or Deputie, or Deputies, and their ſucceſſors, or the major
part of them; as is aforeſaid then preſent, as often as need ſhall be;
the ſaid Statutes, Lawes and Ordinances, ſhall and may exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute and put in
execution as well within our Realme of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as within the ſaid
Realmes, Dominions, Cities &amp; Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and every of them. And for that
divers perſons, our ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, being not brought up in Merchandize, through
their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and lack of knowledge, commit many inconveniencies, we willing
to reſiſt and prevent them, and intending to further the 
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:113934:32"/> expert Merchant in their lawfull and honeſt trade: Will
and by our Regall authority we command, and alſo prohibit and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid by
theſe preſents, that no ſubject of us, our heires, or ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors,
which is not, nor ſhall be by force of theſe preſents, made free of the
ſaid Fellowſhip, ſhall by any maner of means at any time hereafter,
intermeddle in the trade of Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize; or by any means buy and ſell, or
uſe any traffick into the ſaid parts of <hi>Eaſtland,</hi> and countries
aforeſaid, or any of them, (except before excepted) upon pain to incurre our
indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: as alſo to pay ſuch fines and amercements, and to ſuffer
impriſonment, and ſuch other pains due to the tranſgreſſors of of the
ſaid ſtatutes, ordinances and conſtitutions of the ſaid fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip,
or to the ſaid Governor or his Deputy and aſſiſtants aforeſaid,
ſhall ſeem meet and convenient, any law, ſtatute, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, or
ordinance to the contrary thereof, many other things notwithſtanding,
&amp;c.</p>
                                       <p>And do further by theſe preſents inhibit and
forbid all and every our ſubjects, &amp; the ſubjects of us, our heirs
&amp; ſucceſſors, not being licenſed and authorized by vertue of
theſe preſents, to traffick in and to the ſaid Countries, Kingdomes,
Towns, and places before recited, or uſe any manner of trade in or to them,
contrary to the tenor of theſe preſents, upon pain to incurre the
diſpleaſure of us, our heirs, and ſucceſſors, and to be fined,
pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and impriſoned, according to the ſeverall diſcretions and lawes
of the Officers of the ſaid former ſeverall Companies and their
ſucceſſors.</p>
                                       <closer>
                                          <signed>Witneſſe our ſelf</signed>
                                          <dateline>at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> 
                                             <date>the 17. day of Auguſt in in the 21. year
of our reign.</date>
                                          </dateline>
                                       </closer>
                                    </div>
                                 </body>
                              </floatingText>
                           </q>
                           <p>I no ſooner made a ſurvey of this cruell engine,
what intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble breaches and in-rodes it hath continually made upon us,
<hi>but was caſt into a ſudden admiration,</hi> that ſo free a people as
<hi>England</hi> ſhould ſuffer themſelves ſo violently to be <hi>ground
to powder,</hi> which I ſhall illuſtrate to be <hi>treaſonable</hi> in
the practiſers of it, by theſe Poſitions, 1. If to ſurrender a Caſtle
by the Captain of that Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, through feare and cowardize, and not from any
compliance with the enemy, be treaſon; as was adjudged in the Parliament, 1
<hi>Rich.</hi> 2. <hi>Then is this a treaſonable Patent:</hi> For beſides
the place, there is onely a loſſe of the adjacent parts, but by this
Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent our Lawes, Liberties, nay, our very Lives, in purſuance 
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:113934:33"/> 
                              <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                                 <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                              </gap> 
                              <pb n="49" facs="tcp:113934:33"/> 
                              <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                                 <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                              </gap> 
                              <pb n="48" facs="tcp:113934:34"/> of both the former, <hi>are ſubjected to will and
tyrannie,</hi> he that walkes in the exerciſe of freedome, according to Law,
is ſubject to their counter-commands, and to be fined payned, and
impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>and to ſuffer ſuch other puniſhments, as to them
ſhall ſeeme meet and convenient.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>If to kill a Judge upon the Bench be treaſon,
becauſe of malice, not to the perſon, but to the Law; <hi>then is this a
treaſonable Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent;</hi> here is not only a malice to the Law, but a moſt
butcherly weapon-killing and deſtroying of it. Theſe two cannot dwell
to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; for the life of the patent, ſo far as it extends, is the death of
the Law, which ſtops its free courſe for the benefit of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and
makes it meerly a dead letter, <hi>a carkas without a ſoule,</hi> a power
being given to Mr. Governour and his companions, to make Lawes, Statutes, and
Ordinances; <hi>which power is more, and far greater, then belongs to the
chiefe Magiſtrate to give,</hi> or can legally or juſtly be exerciſed by
any <hi>but the Parliament;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not to be received by any
perſon or perſons whatſoever, and certainly thoſe Laws, &amp; all that
Government derived from Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Broad Seal Commiſſion,
are according to the luſts of theſe men, being extrajudiciall, in that they
are above the Sphere of the Law.</p>
                           <p>Secondly, <hi>Contrary to the Law,</hi> if the
endeavouring <hi>the ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the antient Fundamentall Lawes and
Governmant of this Kingdome, and to introduce an arbytrary and tyrannicall
Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be treaſon,</hi> as was adjudged in the caſe of the Earl of
<hi>Straf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> and in the caſe of Sir <hi>Robert Berkly,</hi> by the
firſt Article of impeachment by the Houſe of Commons, <hi>July</hi> 6,
1641. <hi>then is this a treaſonable patent;</hi> for here is not only an
indeavour, <hi>but an actuall ſurrender of both Law and Government,</hi>
which have made <hi>England</hi> a free people; and what more ancient or
fundamentall, then thoſe Laws which gratifie the Commons; and by which they
enjoy their very lives: <hi>Here is an arbytrary Government introduced,</hi>
and put into the hands of thoſe whom the ſubject doth not owne to have any
right of power &amp; rule; and that in ſo high a nature, as can be no
leſſe then <hi>Monarchicall;</hi> for what can a <hi>Monarchicall</hi>
power be, <hi>but to make lawes, and to puniſh the tranſgreſſors
accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thoſe lawes, by confiſcation of goods, impriſonment, or
taking away the life of the vaſſals:</hi> All which, they do by their
patents <pb n="49" facs="tcp:113934:34"/> and certainly this company of Merchants of
<hi>Eaſt-land,</hi> who have practiſed arbytrarily for ſo long a
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                                 <desc>•…</desc>
                              </gap>me, as they have done, againſt
the liberties of the natives, deſerve for all their cruelties to be proceeded
againſt <hi>as publike Delinquents to the State.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="3">3. <hi>As touching their Oath, it is one of the
worſt</hi> I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent) that ever was made, which I ſhal here inſert
for every mans knowledge.</p>
                           <q> 
                              <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                                 <body>
                                    <div type="oath">
                                       <p>YOu ſhall ſwear to be good and true to our
Soveraign Lord the Kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and to his Heires and Succeſsors. you
ſhall be obedient and aſſiſtant to Mr. <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, his Deputy and
Deputies, and Aſſiſtants of Merchants of Eaſt-land.</hi> All
<hi>Statutes and Ordinances, which bee, or ſhall be made by the ſaid
Governor,</hi> or by his Deputies, and Aſsiſtants ſtanding in force; You
ſhall truly hold and keepe, having no ſingular regard to your ſelf, in
hurt or prejudice of the Common-wealth of the ſaid Fellowſhip; You ſhall
heale, and not bewray: and if you ſhall know any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Perſon or
Perſons, which intend any <pb n="50" facs="tcp:113934:35"/> hurt, harme, or prejudice to
our ſaid Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Lord the Kings Majeſty, or unto his Land, or to the
foreſaid Fellowſhip or Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of the ſame, you ſhall give
know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thereof, and do it to be known to the ſaid Governour, or his
Deputy; and you ſhall not colour or free any Forraigners Goods not free of
the ſaid Fellowſhip: All which you ſhall hold and keep to the
utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of your power, or elſe being juſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for making
default in any of the premiſes you ſhall truly from time to time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
orderly demanded, content &amp; pay to the Treaſurer of this Company for the
time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, all and every ſuch mulcts and penalties which have been or
ſhall be limitted, and ſet for the Trangreſſors of the ſame.</p>
                                       <trailer>So God you helpe.</trailer>
                                    </div>
                                 </body>
                              </floatingText>
                           </q>
                           <p>
                              <pb n="51" facs="tcp:113934:35"/>Lieutenant Col. <hi>Lilburn,</hi> in
his late book, called <hi>Innocencie and Truth juſtified,</hi> being an
Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Pryns</hi> book, called <hi>the Lyar confounded,</hi> hath
theſe paſſages, pag. 53. And in the ſecond place, ſeeing they know,
<hi>viz.</hi> the Merchant-Adventurers, <hi>That the Petition of Right doth
condemn the King and his Privie Councell, for making and adminiſtring of
Oaths not made by COMMON CONSENT OF PARLIAMENT; and ſeeing the Parliament, as
they very well know, was lately ſo angry at the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and their
Convocation, for aſſuming to themſelves the boldneſſe to make an
Oath, although they were inveſted with a more colourable authority to
juſtifie them therein, then thoſe can pretend;</hi> how exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary ought
the puniſhment of theſe men to be for their impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and boldneſſe,
<hi>after the knowledge of all this, to force and preſſe upon the free-men
of</hi> England, <hi>an Oath of their own framing and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and to keep
their freedomes from them? becauſe, out of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence they dare not take
them, which at this preſent day is the condition of one Mr. JOHNSON, late
ſervant to Mr. WHITLOCK, one of the Eaſt-Country Monopolizing Merchants,
which is all one in nature with the Monopoly of Merchant Adventurers: And not
onely do they moſt unjuſtly keep my freedome from me, for which I have ſo
often ventured my life in the Northern ſervice this preſent wars,</hi> and
to which, I was born by the Law; although I have ſerved 7. years according to
the Cuſtome of the City of <hi>London,</hi> but moſt inhumanely have taken
from me my place of <hi>Factor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> in the <hi>Eaſt-land;</hi> and
all, becauſe I have rejected their <hi>Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poly</hi> and Diabolicall
<hi>Oath:</hi> and this was the gallant ſervice of Mr. <hi>Burnel</hi>
Governour, and his Aſſociates the 3. <hi>Octob.</hi> 1645. but I except to
ſee Juſtice <hi>(that baniſhed exile)</hi> return in all her glory, and
theſe oppreſſing task-maſters called to a juſt account: For certain I
am, <hi>that the Law never gave them authority to make an Oath,</hi> or to
force it upon my Conſcience; <hi>beſides, the Oath contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth many
perjuries,</hi> in the ſecond branch it ties the ſwearer to be
aſſiſtant to Mr. Governour, and his Confederates, in all their
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt proceedings.</p>
                           <p>In the third Branch, to keepe all their pernicious Lawes
and Ordinances; which Lawes and Ordinances are to deprive the Subject of his
right; and this will not ſatisfie, <hi>but to all that are to be made:</hi> O
intollerable burthen! whither will this bottomleſſe <pb n="52" facs="tcp:113934:36"/>
pit go? here is &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c. and innumerable company of &amp;c. In
the fourth branch; <hi>to keepe all their cozening ſecrets, and under-hand
dealings in the purſuance of their patent.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>And in the fifth branch, <hi>for making default in any
of the premiſes;</hi> that is, for forſwearing himſelf, <hi>which he doth
that keeps it,</hi> aſwell as he that keeps it not, <hi>becauſe he ſwears
not in truth, in judgment, and in righteouſneſſe,</hi> to pay ſuch
mulcts and penalties which have been or ſhall be limitted and ſet for the
tranſgreſſors of the ſame, as if ſuch great crimes could be waſhed
away with a pennance: for my part I am clear in this point, that whoſoever he
bee that bends and yeelds obedience to this or the like Oath, <hi>deſerves
not the name of an Engliſhman:</hi> Surely, their deſignes are (to uſe
the expreſſion of Lieutenant-Colonel <hi>Lilburn,</hi> in page the 54. of
his book, ſpeaking againſt the Merchant-Adventurers) to make
<hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> a Land of ſlavery, ignorance, and beggery, or elſe a Land
of perjury.</p>
                           <p>I have now learned the meaning of the Scripture, Rev.
13.16, 17. <hi>And he cauſeth all both ſmall and great, rich and poor, free
and bond, to receive a mark in their right hand, or in their foreheads, that
none might buy or ſell, ſave he that had the marke, or the name of the
beaſt, or the number of his name:</hi> which relates, as I conceive, to all
Monopolies whatſoever, <hi>ſublata cauſa tollitur effectus,</hi> take but
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way theſe Merchants patents, and all other of the like nature; and there
will a ſudden way appear to the relief of the honeſt, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and
tranquility to the whole Nation: for the effecting wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, if I ſhall but
irritate the courteous Reader, it is price ſufficient for him whoſe
deſire it is not to live, but in the truth.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>THOMAS JOHNSON.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>But for the further evincing of the illegality of theſe
Patentee-Monopolies, I ſhall here inſert a caſe upon the Statute of
Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polies, which was made and reſolved by an able and learned Lawyer &amp;
who had not a little ſhare in the framing &amp; contriving of the ſaid
Statute: which caſe thus followeth:</p>
            <p>IN the 21. year of the raign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> divers
Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of the City of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ondon</hi> obtained a Grant by Letters-Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents <pb n="53" facs="tcp:113934:36"/> from the ſaid Queen, whereby they are incorporate by a ſpeciall
name, <hi>pro ut,</hi> &amp;c. and made a Body politique to have perpetuall
ſucceſſion; with a Grant, that they and their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors may uſe
the traffique and fear of Merchandize, out, of, and from any her Majeſties
Dominions, through the SOVND into SWETHIA, POLAND, and other COVNTRIES: which
Corporation is commonly called the EAST-LAND COMPANY, with a Clauſe in the
ſaid Letters Pattents; that none but they themſelves, and ſuch as they
ſhall think fit (for ſuch Fines and Compoſitions as they ſhall
impoſe, and in ſuch manner and forme as they ſhal direct and allow of)
ſhall trade or traffique through the ſaid SOVND into the ſaid parts of
SWETHIA or POLAND, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In the 20. year of King <hi>CHARLES I. S.</hi> being a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant,
Citizen, and Free-man of the ſaid City of <hi>London,</hi> but not a member,
nor free of the ſaid Incorporation, nor of the ſaid Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land Company,
provideth Engliſh commodities of good and merchantable cloth, well and
ſufficiently wrought, dreſſed and dyed, and ſhippeth, or really
offer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th to ſhip the ſame, to be
car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed from the Port and City of <hi>London</hi> aforeſaid, by way of
trade, traffique, and merchandize, through the ſaid <hi>SOVND</hi> to
<hi>Dant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zick</hi> in <hi>Poland</hi> and maketh, or offereth to make, reall
and due en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try thereof in the Cuſtome-houſe of the Port of <hi>London</hi>
afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; and to pay all Cuſtomes, and other duties and fees any way
payable by Law, for or in reſpect of the ſhipping or entring ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>J. N.</hi> by, upon, and in purſuance of a Warrant or
Command from the ſaid Incorporation of Merchants, or Eaſtland Company,
forbiddeth the ſaid <hi>J. S.</hi> and the Officers of, and in the ſaid
Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome houſe, to make entry of the ſaid goods, of, or for the
co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quetting or cuſtoming of the ſame, and forbiddeth the Maſter &amp;
Marriners of the ſhip, wherein the ſame ſhould be laden or laid aboard,
from taking or ſtowing them aboard in the ſaid ſhip.</p>
            <p>The ſaid <hi>J. S.</hi> perſiſting nevert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eleſſe in his endeavour duly to
enter his ſaid goods, and to coquet and cuſtome the ſame, as to law
appertaineth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:113934:37"/>The ſaid <hi>I. N</hi> by pretext of ſome
Warrant, or command from the ſaid <hi>Incorporation,</hi> or <hi>Eaſtland
Company of Merchants,</hi> groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon their Grant and Letters-Pattents
aforeſaid, ſeizeth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, taketh, carrieth away, and detaineth the ſaid
goods, againſt the will of the ſaid <hi>I. S.</hi> and will not let it
paſſe in the courſe of trade, nor reſtore the ſame to him, upon, and
after reaſonable requeſt thereof made.</p>
            <p>The queſtion is, whether the ſaid <hi>I.</hi> S. may as a
party grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, have his ſpeciall action, upon the Stat. of 21. <hi>Iac.
chap.</hi> 3. concerning Monopolies, againſt the ſaid <hi>I. N.</hi> and
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover his treble dammages, and double coſts; yea, or no.</p>
            <p>Vpon carefull peruſall of the ſaid Statute, as well the
induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or recitall thereof, as the body of the ſame, and the ten
ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Proviſoes therein contained; I am of opinion, that the ſaid
<hi>I. S.</hi> may have his Action upon the ſaid Statute againſt the ſaid
<hi>I. N.</hi> and that he may, and ought to recover his treble dammages, and
double coſts, according to the purport of the ſame Statute.</p>
            <p>My Reaſons are as followeth:</p>
            <p>Firſt, I hold the ſaid Letters-Pattents of 21. <hi>Eliz:</hi>
for ſo much thereof, as concerneth the reſtraint of the Merchants, being
Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of this Realm, from lawfull trading at their pleaſures; to bee a
Monopoly, or matter tending to the inſtituting, erecting, furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, or
countenancing of the ſole uſing of a thing within this Realme, by ſome
men within this Realm, excluding others ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving right to uſe the ſame,
which is a Monopoly, or tending to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſame; and ſo was and is void,
by force of the common Law, <hi>without the helpe of this Statute,</hi> which
doth not in this point introduce or make a new Law; <hi>but only declareth,
vindicateth, and confirmeth the ancient Lawes of the Land, by Judgment of the
Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament;</hi> as appeareth by the words of the ſaid Statute in many
places: namely, in the <hi>inducement to the body of the Act:</hi> in which
inducement, it is recited; <hi>that the Declaration of King</hi> James,
<hi>in</hi> 
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:113934:37"/> 1610. (That all Grants of Monopolies were
contrary to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Lawes) <hi>is conſonant and agreeable to the
ancient and funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Lawes of this Realm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the <hi>body of the Act,</hi> the word <hi>[declared]</hi>
is put before the word <hi>[enacted.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the principall words of the Act run thus, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That Monopolies, and all Commiſſions, Grants, Licences,
Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and Letters Pattents, made, or to be made, of, or for the ſole
u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of any thing within the Realm, and all Proclamations, Reſtraints
Warrants of Aſſiſtances, and all other matters and things whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,
any way tending as aforeſaid, are ALTOGETHER contrary to the Lawes of this
Realm, and ſo are, and ſhall be utterly void, and of none effect, and in no
wiſe to be put in ure or execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which ſaid leading words, <hi>viz. That they are contrary to the
lawes;</hi> and the ſaid concluſive words, <hi>viz. and ſo</hi> (that is,
in true ſence; becavſe they are contrary to the Lawes) <hi>they are
void;</hi> do manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew, that without the help of this Law, the
ſaid Letters Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents and all others of like nature were void. And the
declaratory part of the ſtattutes was made only for the better enlightning of
weaker judgments, or to arme the Miniſters of Juſtice with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence and
ſecurity, to deliver and adjudge the Law in ſuch par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars of this
nature, as might after come in queſtion againſt the importunity of
powerfull Courtiers, when there was a direct written text of Statute-Law, which
they might inſiſt upon more perſpicuous then the fundamentall common-law,
and generall good cuſtome of the Realm was, while being unwritten, it
reſted onely in the breaſts of thoſe who are the diſpenſers of it,
every Judicatory in its proper turn.</p>
            <p>After the Declaratory part of the ſaid Statute, followeth the
new proviſionall introductive part of it; whereby (omitting purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in
this place, the word <hi>declared</hi>) it is further enacted, <hi>That if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
perſon ſhall be hindered, grieved, diſturbed, or diſquieted, or his, or
their goods, or chattels any way ſeized, attached, diſtrained, taken,
carryed away, or detained by occaſion or pretext of any Monopoly, or of any
ſuch Commiſſion, Grant, Licence, Power, Liberty, Faculty;
Letters-Pattents, Proclamation, Inhibition, Reſtraint, Warrant of
Aſſiſtance, or other matter or thing tending as aforeſaid (as in
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:113934:38"/> ſaid Act
is mentioned) and will ſue to be relieved in or for any the premiſes, That
then, and in every ſuch caſe, the ſame perſon and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſhall
and may have his and their remedy for the ſame at the common-law in the
Kings-Bench, Common-Pleas, or Exchequer, by any Action or Actions, to be
grounds upon this Statute againſt him by whom he ſhall be ſo hindered,
&amp;c. or by whom his goods ſhall be ſo ſeized, &amp;c. and recover
TREBLE DAMMAGES and DOVBLE COSTS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in ſuch ſuite, as for the ſtaying thereof, no
priviledge, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, or order of reſtraint, ſhall be prayed, granted
admitted, or allowed, nor any more then one imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ance, with a Clauſe of <hi>praemunire, pro ut,</hi>
&amp;c.</p>
            <p>And by this Clauſe, in the next place I obſerve clearly, that
the ſaid <hi>I. S.</hi> as the caſe is put, is to have his ſpeciall
action upon the ſaid Statute againſt the ſaid <hi>I. N.</hi> to recover
his <hi>treble dammages, and double coſts,</hi> and is not to be hindered
from his proceeding by any priviledge, or order of reſtraint, &amp;c. In
caſe the 5. of the 10. proviſoes in the ſaid Act contained, do not
ſufficiently extend to exempt the ſaid <hi>J.</hi>S. or his caſe, out of
the declaratory part, and out of the new proviſionall and introductive part
of the ſaid Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute.</p>
            <p>The effectuall words of the ſaid fifth proviſoe, are onely
theſe, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q> Provided alſo, and it is hereby further intended, declared and
enacted; that this Act, or any thing therein contained, ſhall not extend or
be prejudiciall to the City of <hi>London,</hi> for, or concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning any Grants,
Charters, or Letters-Pattents, to them made or granted, or for, or concerning
any cuſtome or cuſtomes, uſed by or within the ſame, or unto any
Corporations, Companies, or Fellowſhips, of any Art, Trade, Occupation, or
Myſtery, or to any Companies, or Societies of Merchants within this Realm
erected for the maintenance, enlargement, or ordering of any Trade or
Merchandize: But that the ſame Charters, Cuſtomes, Corporations, Companies,
Fellowſhips, and Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and their
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and priviledges, powers and
immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſhall be and continue of ſuch force and effect, as they were
BEFORE THE MAKING OF THIS ACT, <pb n="57" facs="tcp:113934:38"/> and of none other, any
thing before in this Act contained to the contrary, in any wiſe
notwithſtanding.</q>
            <p>And it ſeemeth to me, that this fifth <hi>Proviſo</hi> doth
neither in words nor in meaning exempt the ſaid <hi>I. S.</hi> or his caſe,
out of, or from the Declaratory part, or out of, or from the Proviſionall and
Introductive part of the ſaid Statute: Becauſe as to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claratory part,
the ſaid <hi>proviſo</hi> being repugna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the body of the act, muſt
needs be, &amp; is, in true co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtruction of law, utterly void, as being
therein totally repugnant to the declaratory part of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Statute.
For to ſay that all <hi>Monopolies</hi> and all Grants of ſuch and ſuch
natures, <hi>are void by law,</hi> and yet to conclude that a particular
<hi>Monopoly</hi> or Grant for ſole uſing of a thing &amp;c. which by Law
is a <hi>Monopoly,</hi> and ſo declared, is neuertheleſſe no
<hi>Monopoly,</hi> or is not void, is irreconcileably repugnant, and
conſequently the ſaid <hi>Proviſo,</hi> or <hi>Exception,</hi> being of
ſuch repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant nature, as aforeſaid, is in Law void.</p>
            <p>And if it be objected by way of queſtion, <hi>Why then was the
Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſo inſerted?</hi> The true &amp; ſufficient anſwer is eaſie,
namely, That it was inſerted to ſecure the city &amp; Merchants who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it did
or might concern of thus much (which was all the right that was inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them)
That if their Charters or Cuſtomes were in all, of in part good and valid in
Law, before the making of this Statute; then in the points of ſuch their
force and validity, this Statute ſhould not make them worſe; but leave them
as they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>And whereas it may be objected, That though the ſaid
<hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo</hi> cannot exempt them out of the Declaratory Premiſes and
bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Act, yet it might exempt them from the new proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall and
Introductive part of the Act, namely, from being lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to <hi>treble
dammages, and double coſts,</hi> and from incurring the paines, penalties,
and forfeitures of the Statute of <hi>Proviſion</hi> and <hi>Premunire,</hi>
and that the ſaid proviſo ſhall take effect to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, as by law
it may, rather then be rejected as utterly void, &amp; impertinent; I conceive
nevertheleſſe, that this objection is of little force, becauſe there was
neither meaning in the Law-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers ſo to exempt them, nor are there any words
in the Act ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing their intention ſo to bee, as appeareth by the
very act it ſelfe, (the beſt expoſitor of the true meaning of it ſelfe)
in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring <pb n="58" facs="tcp:113934:39"/> this <hi>proviſo</hi> with the other parts
and <hi>proviſoes</hi> of and in the ſaid act; which are differently penned
from this <hi>proviſo,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by doe ſhew the different meaning of
the Law-makers in and concerning the <hi>Subject matter</hi> of this, and the
ſubject matter of the ſaid other <hi>Proviſoes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the 6. 7, 8. 9. and 10. <hi>proviſoes</hi> in the ſaid
act, are pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with apt and ſtrong words in the beginning of every of them,

<q rend="inline">That it is provided and enacted that the ſaid
act, or any penalty or forfeiture before mentioned, ſhal not extend to
Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters patents, or grants concerning Printing, Salt-peter, Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder,
caſting or making of Ordnance, ſhot for Ordnance, Offices erected then in
being, and not decryed, Allum, Allum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines, the fellowſhip of the Hoaſtmen
of <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> upon <hi>Tyne,</hi> the licencing of Tavernes, the
making of glaſſe, the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation of Calves-skins, the making of
ſmalt, and the mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Iron-ore with Sea-cole or pit-cole. All which
laſt mentioned proviſoes, except onely the eighth, doe conclude with words,
That the ſaid excepted letters Patents, and grants ſhall be as free from
the proviſions, penalties, &amp; forfeitures con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the ſaid
act,</q> as if the ſaid act had never been had or made; whereas the ſaid
fifth proviſo hath no ſuch apt or effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall words either in the beginning
or concluſion thereof. And though it be true, that the words in the beginning
of the fifth proviſo, are, 
<q rend="inline">That the act, or any thing therein contained
ſhall not extend or be prejudiciall to the Citie of <hi>London,</hi> or to
ſuch grants or letters patents, as that proviſo referreth unto, which are
large enough to exempt them from all proviſions, diſable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, penalties
and forfeitures in the ſaid act,</q> as the ſame are parcell of, and
contained in the ſaid act; yet the word <hi>[prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall]</hi> annexed to
that word <hi>[extend]</hi> and the words in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of the ſaid
fifth proviſo, which are of an explanatory and qualifying nature, doe ſo
reconcile the ſaid proviſo to the body of the act, that upon the whole
matter it is evident, the ſaid <hi>Grants</hi> and <hi>Letters patents,</hi>
by the meaning of the Law makers well couched, yet fully expreſſed in their
words, are by the ſaid proviſo ſo and in ſuch ſort onely excepted
from prejudice by the extent of the <hi>body of the Act</hi> thereunto, that
they ſhal be and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue of ſuch force and effect in law, and of <hi>none
other,</hi> as they <pb n="59" facs="tcp:113934:39"/> were before the making of the ſaid
act, which was juſt none at all in law, and therefore are now in every
reſpect utterly void in law, (being by this act left without any Cloke, or
Fig-leafe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers) any proviſion in the ſaid act to the contrary
notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: but not to be free from the declarations, penalties and
for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures in the act contained, as if the act had never been had or made.
For, to be of force as they were <hi>before the Act,</hi> is one thing, and to
be as free as if <hi>the Act had never been,</hi> is another thing. And it is
not to be conceived, that the ſaid ſeveral <hi>proviſoes</hi> in the
ſaid act contained, came to be ſo differently penned by meer acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, but
by deliberate &amp; wel-adviſed purpoſe, which is very co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable for
the true interpretatio of the ſaid act For if the words <hi>[or be
prejudiciall]</hi> be not explanatory, they are void &amp; ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: for
the word <hi>[ſhall not extend]</hi> was ſufficient to except the intended
grants and <hi>Letters Patents,</hi> out of the proviſion of the <hi>body of
the Act</hi> to all purpoſes, if ſo large exception had been intended, as
it was not; and therefore the words <hi>(or be prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall)</hi> which are
ſubjoyned, muſt needs be explanatory, or quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifying, rather then
rejected as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>terly void: and then
the true ſenſe of both words united in right conſtruction, is, <hi>That
the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions of the Statute ſhall not extend to the ſaid grants, or
Letters patents, to due unto them, or bring upon them any prejudice,</hi> that
is, any wrong 
<note n="*" place="margin">Note well.</note> by taking away the good
or valid part thereof, or by making them of leſſe force or effect then they
were before the Statute, which had been a prejudice or wrong unto them; but no
prejudice or wrong is done to the Letters patents, by giving a large and good
remedie to parties grieved by offences to be done by colour of the
<hi>ineffectuall parts,</hi> or clauſes of ſuch Grants, or Letters patents,
<hi>which were void from the beginning.</hi> And note, this is not a popular
and penall law in this point, <hi>but onely a law conferring reliefe upon
parties grieved,</hi> and to be largely interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted accordingly.</p>
            <p>And whereas it may be objected, <hi>That in the ſaid Act there
a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> foure other proviſoes
precedent to the ſaid proviſo concencerning London,</hi> and the Societies
and Companies of Merchants of this Realm, erected for the maintenance,
enlargement, or ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ing of trade,
or Merchandize, for the excepting thereof, out of,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> from the ſaid act, or out of
or from the declarations of and in the <pb n="60" facs="tcp:113934:40"/> ſaid Act, which
in the entrance into the ſaid proviſoes, or at the concluſion thereof,
have no words to except the particulars in thoſe proviſoes ſpecified or
deſcribed from the proviſions, penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, &amp; forfeiture, is contained
in the body or purview of the ſaid act; yet it were hard to think ſuch
perſons as by pretext of letters patents, or grants of the King, or his
predeceſſors in that behalfe made with clauſes in them
<hi>(peradventure)</hi> reſtraining all men without the conſent of the
<hi>Patentees, or their aſſignes,</hi> from exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing ſuch
particulars, ſhould hinder men from their trade, in ſuch ſort onely as
before the making of the ſaid Statute they uſed without controll to doe,
ſhould onely for ſo hindering or diſquieting a man, or for ſeizing or
taking away of his goods after the ſaid Statute bee expoſed to an action or
ſuit, wherein they ſhould be liable to pay treble dammages, and double
coſts.</p>
            <p>It is by way of diſtinction to be anſwered; 
<q rend="inline">That if the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the law had ſo intended,
they would have uſed the like words in this fifth proviſo, as they did in
foure of the five laſt proviſoes,</q> and their not uſing the ſame,
importeth ſtrongly that they meant not any ſuch matter. 
<q rend="inline">Alſo, the concluſion of the ſaid fifth
proviſo being (as in effect) I have noted before, with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planatory
clauſe, viz. that the ſaid Letters patents, &amp;c. concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſuch
Societies and Companies of Merchants, ſhould be &amp; continue of ſuch
force &amp; effect as they were before, &amp; of none other.</q> Their force
and effect before the Statute, was, that they were good to incorporate the
ſaid Societies and Companies of Merchants, and of effect alſo to enable
them to have perpetuall ſucceſſion, and to make ordinances and
conſtitutions, <hi>not repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the law of the Realm;</hi> which no
Corporation in <hi>England</hi> can doe, no not <hi>London</hi> it ſelfe, as
Sir <hi>Edward Cook affirms</hi> in the fourth part of his <hi>Inſtitutes,
fol.</hi> 249. <hi>and chap.</hi> 50. And therefore all thoſe <hi>Ordinances,
Lawes and Orders</hi> made by the Court of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen, and Common Councell
of London,</hi> or by any of the Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hoods, or Patentee-Mynopolizing Corporations of Drapers, Mercers,
Grocers, Cloath-workers, and Merchants of what Countrey ſoever, <hi>that are
contrary to the known, univerſall, and fundamentall law of the land,</hi> are
abſolutely and utterly void, and not in the leſt to be obeyed, and
puniſhable is he that ſhall put <pb n="61" facs="tcp:113934:40"/> them in execution, and
ought to bee reputed an enemy to the Lawes and Liberties of <hi>England;</hi>
with other <hi>legall benefits,</hi> and of ſuch force and effect they
ſtill are, by the <hi>declaratory</hi> operation of the ſaid
<hi>proviſo;</hi> wherewith the ſaid <hi>proviſo</hi> is aptly and fully
ſatisfied, and no need to extend the ſame to exempt perſons offending (by
colour of ſuch <hi>Grants,</hi> or <hi>Letters Patents,</hi> out of, and from
the penalties or forfeitures inflicted by the act, by <hi>pretext of the
illegall part of ſuch letters Patents</hi> and Grants, the rather for that
this is a beneficiall law, made for the good of the Common-wealth, and FOR
FREEDOME AND LI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BERTY OF TRADE, and of the free <hi>Subjects</hi> of the Realm
in that behalfe: and therefore is to be largely interpreted for advancement of
the generall remedy intended; and ſtrictly to be interpreted in all points
and particulars tending to abridge or reſtrain that good remedy. Alſo there
are two main differences betwixt the ſaid fifth <hi>proviſo,</hi> and the
foure firſt <hi>proviſoes</hi> in the ſaid <hi>Act.</hi> For the firſt
two of the ſaid four <hi>proviſoes,</hi> concerning <hi>letters
patents</hi> of priviledge, have in them theſe words, the firſt of them,
<hi>that the ſaid Declarations in the act ſhould not extend to ſuch
letters Patents formerly made;</hi> &amp; the ſecond of them, <hi>to ſuch
letters Patents futu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ely made
concerning the ſole makong or working of new Manufactures to the firſt and
true inventers thereof for a reaſonable time of</hi> 21. <hi>yeares,</hi> or
under, for ſuch Letters Patents granted <hi>before the Statute;</hi> or for
<hi>fourteen yeares,</hi> or under, to bee granted after the <hi>Statute:</hi>
foureteen yeares being but the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon time of two ordinary Apprentiſhips.
Which kind of <hi>let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Patents</hi> granted as a juſt reward to the
proper perſon or his aſſignes for and in reſpect of <hi>a meer new and
good invention,</hi> not miſchievous to the State, <hi>nor hurtfull to
Trade,</hi> nor <hi>generally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenient,</hi> was never counted an
<hi>illegal monopoly.</hi> And therefore being qualified, as in the ſaid
<hi>proviſoes,</hi> and limited to the tearms of 21. and 14. <hi>yeares,</hi>
as aforeſaid, <hi>were not repugnant to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claratory part, or main body
of the Statute,</hi> but wel conſiſtent with the ſame, being
<hi>reconcileable and reconciled</hi> by reaſonable <hi>conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction;</hi>
whereas the <hi>Leters Patents</hi> and <hi>Grants</hi> in the ſaid <hi>fifth
proviſo, are perpetuall:</hi> and ſo farre as they tend to RESTRA<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>N FREE TRADE, and to appropriate it
ſolely to ſome few perſons, are MISCHIEVOUS MONOPOLIES, 
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:113934:41"/> 
               <hi>hurtfull to the State, generally inconvenient,</hi>
and by the ſaid proviſoe not limitted to have continuance for any time or
number of 21. or 14. yeares, or other terme whatſoever, nor otherwiſe in
any ſort, conſiſtent with the body of the Act, and therefore either the
Act muſt be void, or the ſaid proviſoe, which being ſo, it followeth by
the cleare rule for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Statutes, that the ſaid 5.
proviſoe, and not the body of the Act, is to be rejected as repugnant and
voyd.</p>
            <p>Touching the third proviſoe, it is of ſo particular and
ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all a nature, that no argument can be drawne from the words, or from
the manner or forme thereof, towards the conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſaid 5.
proviſoe; for the ſaid third proviſoe is onely concerning priviledges,
powers, or authorities formerly gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Act of Parliament, which (not being
unlawfull in the creation) however they might tend to give the ſole uſing
of ſome things to ſome particular perſons, becauſe they were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected
by act of Parliament, to which all men in Law being parties are in Law
concluded &amp; bound thereby, alwayes provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded they be not contrary to the
fundamentall Lawes of the Kingdome, for the Parliament by their own
confeſſion are choſen and truſted by us to provide for our weale but
not for our woe, Book. Declar. pag. 150. and therefore all the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances and
orders of late unduly obtained from the preſent Parliament, by the Turky
Merchants, Merchant-Adventurers, <hi>Greenland</hi> Merchants, or any other
whatſoever; for the hindering of every free <hi>Engliſhman</hi> to trade
into any place whatſoever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas, or for the ſole ingroſſing
it into the hands of ſuch and ſuch men, is altogether contrary to the
juſt fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Lawes of the Land, and ſo altogether illegall,
unbinding, and ought not in the leaſt to be obeyed, and I know no reaſon
but the executers of them may as juſtly be put to death as Traytors, for
indeavoring the ſubverſion of the fundamentall Lawes of the Land, as
Juſtice <hi>Empſon,</hi> and Juſtice <hi>Dudloy,</hi> were in the firſt
yeare of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. Speed. fol. 978. 983. Martin fol. 353. 355. 356. For
their oppreſſions, and innovating cruelties, exerciſed upon the bodies
and goods of many of the freemen of <hi>England,</hi> by coullor of an unjuſt
and illegall Act of Parliament made in the 11. yeare of <hi>H.</hi> 7. Chap. 3.
which Law, <pb n="63" facs="tcp:113934:41"/> ſaith learned, Sir <hi>Edward Cooke</hi> in
the ſecond part of his inſtitutes fol. 51. was made againſt the antient
and juſt fundamentall Law of the 29. Chapter of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> yea in
the very face of it, and therefore he calles it (though an Act of Parliament)
an unjuſt and injurious Act, ſo that a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament cannot <hi>de jure</hi>
do what they pleaſe, although <hi>de facto</hi> ſometimes they do it, which
is moſt unjuſt in them ſo to doe.</p>
            <p>This third proviſoe was inſerted in caution leſt this latter
generall declaratory Act being contrary to ſuch former parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Acts,
qualified as before ſhould amount to a repeale thereof; which by the makers
of this law was not intended; and this proviſoe inſerted to make due
proviſion according to ſuch their true meaning.</p>
            <p>And touching the 4. proviſoe concerning privy Seales, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abling
Judges in certaine caſes to compound, it relateth not at all to that part of
this Act concerning <hi>Monopolies,</hi> but to the other part of it, which
concerneth the diſpenſation with penall Lawes, and the forfeiture<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thereof; as by the diſtinct parts of
the Act, <hi>reddendo ſingula ſingulis,</hi> doth manifeſtly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare,
whereby no argument can be drawne from the matter or words, or from the manner
or forme of this proviſoe, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the conſtruing of the ſaid 5.
prouiſoe, which onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lateth to, and concerneth that part of the Act,
which treateth of <hi>Monopolies.</hi> And therefore upon the whole matter for
the reaſons aforeſaid, I am of opinion, that the ſaid letters-pattents of
21. <hi>Eliz.</hi> and all ſuch like are within the compaſſe of the
ſaid Act, and thereby in the body of the ſame, <hi>declared to be a
Monopoly, and are not by the ſaid</hi> 5. <hi>proviſoe, excepted or
preſerved from or againſt the proviſion, penalties, or forfeitures of and
in the ſaid Act contained; But that the ſaid I. S. MAY HAVE SVCH ACTION FOR
TREBLE DAMMAGES AND DOVBLE COSTS AS AFORESAID.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having unto this paraphraſe upon the Statute of
<hi>Monopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies,</hi> joyned ſome Marginall notes of my own, the better to
cleare ſome things contained in it; I ſhall heere inſert you Mr.
<hi>William Sycks</hi> his moſt excellent <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> to the
Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, delivered with his own hands to the <hi>Members</hi> thereof, 
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:113934:42"/> in <hi>March</hi> 1645. immediataly after he, and Mr.
<hi>Thomas Iohnſon Merchant</hi> had delivered a moſt excellent and gallant
<hi>Petition</hi> to them, the Copy of which you may reade in my late printed
booke, called <hi>Londons Liberty in Chaines diſcovered,</hi> pag. 43. 44.
45. and the end wherefore I inſert this <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> here, is
becauſe I hope thereby to provoke you eſpecially; <hi>(O ye Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons, or
Commons of London)</hi> to revive his <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> againe, that ſo
you your ſelves, may be inſtruments to procure unto your ſelves, and your
poſterities, that extraordinary benefit (and inrichment to this whole
Kingdome) free trade and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick, which he (though free of the
Merchant-Adventurers Corporation) with ſo much true zeale, honeſty, and
importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate earneſtneſſe, laboured to procure for you, but could
not.</p>
            <p>Onely this I muſt tell you, he followed it ſo cloſe that by
his meanes Collonel <hi>Alexander Rigby, that heroicall, true, and cordiall
lover of his Country,</hi> had prepared to my knowledge the draught of an
Ordinance, <hi>for ever to diſtroy all Monopolies, and abſolutely to ſet
Trade free,</hi> but for want of more helpe then he had, could not then get it
on in the Houſe, which by a new Petition from you (ſo many gallant and
honeſt new Members being choſen ſince into the Houſe) now he eaſily
may: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for your own good and benefit as well as for the generall good
and benefit of the whole Kingdome, and all our poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, <hi>I with all
earneſtneſſe and importunitie in reat you with the ſtrength of zeal,
and reſolved reſolution, forthwith unanimouſly to petition for the
reſtoring of free Trade, and deſtroying of all illegall Monopolies</hi> of
what kind ſoever, and alſo for the ſevere and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary puniſhment of
all (the Ringleaders eſpecially) that have exerciſed them: that ſo the
<hi>Generations to come may be terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied from the indeavouring the
deſtruction of the fundamentall, and rationall eſtabliſhed Law and
Liberties of</hi> England.</p>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:113934:42"/> 
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="remonstrance">
                        <head>To the Right Honorable the high Court of Parliament;
The humble Remonſtrance of <hi>VVILLIAM SYKES</hi> Merchant, for free Trade
in tranſporting &amp; importing of lawfull and needfull commodities.</head>
                        <p>VVHereas of late the Remonſtrant, and <hi>Thomas
Johnſon</hi> Merchant, for themſelves, and on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of all the
free-men of <hi>England,</hi> did petition both Houſes of Parliament for
<hi>Free Trade;</hi> which they are confident is the Common-wealths
BIRTH-RIGHT, <hi>and reparations for wrongs done by thoſe Ingroſſers and
Monopolizers,</hi> who by vertue of Patents, have been, and are ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of
that hereditable right, as the <hi>Company of Merchant-Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturers</hi> have
done to <hi>Cisizens for</hi> 100. <abbr>l.</abbr> a man, and to Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey
people for 50. <abbr>l.</abbr> 
                           <hi>a man.</hi> The like may be ſaid of the
<hi>Company</hi> of <hi>Eaſt-countrey Merchants, Muſcovia Merchants, Turkie
Merchants,</hi> and other <hi>Companies of Merchants,</hi> who have for a long
time practiſed this way of <hi>trade-ſelling,</hi> and
<hi>Monopolizing,</hi> to the great grievance of the people, and detriment to
FREE TRADE, both at home and abroad.</p>
                        <p>Which Petition was preſented to moſt <hi>Members of
both Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and diſperſed into the ſeverall <hi>Counties</hi> of
<hi>England,</hi> that this honorable <hi>Court</hi> may no longer delay the
diſcharge of their truſt, but ſpeedily improve their power to reſcue
FREE TRADE <pb n="64" facs="tcp:113934:43"/> 
                           <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                              <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb facs="tcp:113934:43"/> 
                           <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                              <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <pb facs="tcp:113934:44"/>
from ſuch <hi>Liberty-deſtroyers</hi> and <hi>Trade-ingroſſers,</hi>
and that the <hi>people</hi> may the better know for what <hi>end</hi> and
<hi>purpoſe</hi> they have adventured their <hi>lives</hi> and
<hi>eſtates</hi> in theſe preſent warres.</p>
                        <p>Yet the ſaid Petition is not ſo much as publickly read
in either Houſe of Parliament, far leſſe debated or anſwered, though
the <hi>Common-wealth be ſo much concerned in it,</hi> as in nothing more, if
the <hi>people</hi> knew their <hi>right and freedome,</hi> which this
preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament hath confirmed, by the confirmation of <hi>Magna
Charta,</hi> and by the executing of juſtice on the Earle of
<hi>Strafford</hi> for his exerciſing <hi>arbitrary government againſt the
freedome of England;</hi> therefore the <hi>Remonstrant</hi> doth conceive,
that hee is bound in duty to <hi>follow the ſaid petition with this
Remonſtrance,</hi> which he was emboldned to preſent for theſe two
enſuing reaſons, and to anſwer ſome <hi>objections,</hi> referring the
concluſion to a ſerious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. The firſt reaſon is <hi>drawn from
the ſecond Table of Gods law,</hi> which commands us to love our neighbour as
our ſelves: This BIRTH-RIGHT OF FREE TRADE <hi>being as well our neighbours
right as our own,</hi> therefore we petitioned as well for our neighbours, as
for our ſelves.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2. The ſecond reaſon <hi>is drawn
from the intent of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation,</hi> which we ſolemnly took in the
preſence of Almighty God, <hi>To maintain the right and priviledge of the
people with our lives and eſtates;</hi> this <hi>Free trade being all mens
right and priviledge</hi> as well as our own, upon that ground we were moved to
<hi>petition</hi> as well for their right of <hi>Free Trade,</hi> as for our
own.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Obj.</hi> 1. But theſe Companies have been of long
ſtanding.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Anſ.</hi> So have the Prelats, and ſo much the
more wrong done to the Common-wealth, and therefore ſo much the greater need
to be put down. For although robbing and taking of purſes upon the high way,
be of ancient ſtanding, yet it doth not thereupon follow that ſuch a
practice is ever the lawfuller.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Ob.</hi> 2. But <hi>Magna Charta</hi> doth continue
Biſhops. (But I ſay, <hi>Magna Charta</hi> doth not eſtabliſh
Biſhops, but onely the liberties and rights of the Church of
<hi>England:</hi> and what thoſe are, the Scripture doth beſt tell us. And
although Biſhops be taken away, yet the liberties of the Church
eſtabliſhed by <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> to this very day remain,) And admits
tranſportation of wooll.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb facs="tcp:113934:44"/>
                           <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is one thing to pull down
Biſhops, and make an Act a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt tranſporting of wool, <hi>being the
deſire and for the good of all;</hi> but it is another thing <hi>to take away
the peoples Birth-right, FREE TRADE, without their conſent,</hi> and to their
prejudice, yea and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>many petitions of many thouſands in many
Parliaments</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred for the reſcuing of that right, and reparations
for the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries wrongs.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Obj.</hi> 3, But <hi>Free trade will be deſtructive
to the Common-wealth.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Anſ.</hi> It will bee no more deſtructive to
<hi>Eastland, Muſcovia, Turkie,</hi> the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> and other
places, then it is for <hi>France, Spain, Ireland, Portugal,</hi> and
<hi>Scotland,</hi> which is none at all.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Obj.</hi> 4. But <hi>Cloath</hi> is of another and
better nature then Wine, &amp;c. which are forraigne commodities.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Anſ.</hi> The greater is the wrong, <hi>it being the
grand in-land com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity,</hi> ſo that all other <hi>Patents</hi> and
<hi>Monopolies</hi> may bee better renewed, then this continued.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Obj.</hi> 5. But <hi>Clothiers,</hi> and the like men,
have not knowledge to manage this <hi>Free Trade.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Anſ.</hi> If it were ſo (as it is not) yet the
ſame is occaſioned by theſe <hi>theeves and robbers,</hi> that cunningly
and ſecretly by a faire but unjuſt and deceitfull pretence,
<hi>ſteale</hi> the Common-wealths right, ſo as they are deprived of that
opportunity to educate their children and ſervants, which may enable them to
manage that priviledge of <hi>Free Trade.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Obj.</hi> 6. But they are againſt government, and
would walk diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Anſ.</hi> No, we would have both government and
order in a ſolid and juſt way, but we are againſt helliſh oaths,
unlawful fines, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full orders, falſe impriſonment, law and
right-ſellers, all which are practiſed by theſe
<hi>Trade-ingroſſers,</hi> as will appeare by good teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Obj.</hi> 7. But no man hath followed the
petition.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Anſ.</hi> Is it not the duty of every Truſtee in
the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons to proſecute the <hi>Common-wealths right,</hi> and
peoples privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge? But if that be the hinderance, it is the humble deſire
of the <hi>Remonſtrant,</hi> that Mr. <hi>Rigby,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Martin</hi>
may be appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to draw up a full <hi>Ordinance</hi> without delay, that hee
or they, whoſoever they be, under what pretence or fraud ſoever, may bee 
<pb facs="tcp:113934:45"/> 
                           <hi>accurſed that removes his neighbours land-mark (his
Birth-right, or Free trade)</hi> and that the Commons houſe may approve
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves faithfull, and worthy the Common-wealths truſt, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to the ſolemne proteſtation, to bring to exemplary and condigne
puniſhment, thoſe who have been theeves and robbers in this kind; and
according to an order made this preſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it is earneſtly
deſired, that the Houſe may be purged of all ſuch as are Patentees,
Monopolizers, Trade-ingroſſers, Sellers of peoples right, and deſtroyers
of the <hi>Free Trade.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>And alſo out of all other places of publick truſt
under the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whether in the <hi>Cuſtome-houſe, Commiſſion of
Exciſe, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees in City or Countrey, Soldiery, or other government, as
She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs, Treaſurers, Majors, Aldermen,</hi> and the like, who are not
worthy to be continued in any <hi>Common-wealths truſt;</hi> &amp; ſo much
the more, by how much the longer they have practiſed ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull
<hi>robbery,</hi> and to let all ſuch as have been wronged by theſe kind of
men, have freedom with reſpect and countenance, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute againſt
theſe Caterpillers, for due reparations, according to the wrongs done by them
and their Predeceſſors.</p>
                        <p>And if the <hi>Parliament</hi> would have the free people
to fight for them, as they have willingly done, by venturing their lives and
e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates freely, to maintain their power and priviledge <hi>againſt the
common enemy;</hi> then let that power bee improved and laid out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain <hi>for
the right and priviledge of the ſaid people,</hi> to reſcue and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover
their <hi>Birth-right (Free Trade)</hi> out of the hands of thoſe <hi>greedy
and ſubtile ſpoylers,</hi> yea and <hi>grinders of the faces of the
poore.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>If any further objection be made againſt <hi>Free
trade;</hi> then it is earneſtly deſired that the <hi>Houſe of Commons
would anſwer it them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> as parties in behalfe of the <hi>free
people,</hi> who have called them to <hi>that truſt for that end;</hi> or
otherwiſe let the mind &amp; ſenſe of the <hi>common people in every
County and Corporation</hi> (all <hi>Englond</hi> over) be produced, and let it
go upon that, in which way the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrant</hi> is perſwaded, that a
hundred to one will bee fot <hi>Free Trade.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>So hoping this high and <hi>Honorable Court</hi> will have
due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the premiſes, in all <hi>dutifull acknowledgement;</hi> the
<hi>Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrant</hi> ſhall deſire to prove himſelfe the
<hi>Common-wealths ſervant,</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>William Sykes.</signed> 
                           <dateline>
                              <date>March
20. 1645.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
